<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the Treatise of monarchy, containing an answer to Dr Fernes reply; also, a more full discovery of three maine points; 1. The ordinance of God in supremacie. 2. The nature and kinds of limitation. 3. The causes and meanes of limitation in governments. Done by the authour of the former treatise.</title>
            <author>Hunton, Philip, 1604?-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E39_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 7:E39[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the Treatise of monarchy, containing an answer to Dr Fernes reply; also, a more full discovery of three maine points; 1. The ordinance of God in supremacie. 2. The nature and kinds of limitation. 3. The causes and meanes of limitation in governments. Done by the authour of the former treatise.</title>
                  <author>Hunton, Philip, 1604?-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 [i.e. 70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Iohn Bellamy, and are to be sould at his shop at the signe of the three Golden-Lyons in Cornehill neare the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XLIV. [1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Philip Hunton.  Cf. Thomason Coll.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferne, H. --  (Henry), 1602-1662. --  Conscience satisfied.</term>
               <term>Hunton, Philip, 1604?-1682. --  Treatise of monarchy.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE Treatiſe of Monarchy, CONTAINING An Anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Fernes</hi> Reply; ALSO, A more full Diſcovery of Three maine Points;
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Ordinance of God in Supremacie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Nature and Kinds of Limitation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The Cauſes and Meanes of Limitation in Governments.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Done by the Authour of the former Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamy,</hi> and are to be ſould at his Shop at the Signe of the three Golden-Lyons in Cornehill neare the Royall-Exchange, M.DC.XLIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:155066:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155066:2"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE Treatiſe of Monarchie.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eruſing with a ſad heart and conſcience, deſirous of Information the Papers made publike by the Defenders of both ſides in this wofull diviſion; I found divers of them running out into irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable extreames: among which this <hi>Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> the Authour of the fuller Anſwer, and the Divines plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for Defenſive Armes were the chief. In which I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there were paſſages contrary to all true policie, and the particular Frame of this State. Hereon a deſire of allaying mens ſpirits, and reducing them to a moderate compliance in one Truth induced me to a compoſing of that Treatiſe, In which how farre I have attained my ayme, I leave it to the world to judge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:155066:3"/>But it fals out with me, as it did with <hi>Moſes</hi> endeavouring to ſet at one his contentious Brethren, I have hard words and cenſures laid on me for my labour. This Doctour tels me, I have ſowne ſeeds of ſedition, opened a way to Rebellion, and termes me an engaged man. But to whom I am engaged, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to Truth, I know not: Engaged indeed I am to defend the Kings Supremacie againſt one part by my <hi>Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> and engaged to defend the Priviledges of Parliament, and lawfull Liberties of the Subject, againſt the other part, by my <hi>Protestation:</hi> beyond theſe I know none, and perhaps if this <hi>cenſurer</hi> knew my condition, he would acknowledge as much. No, thoſe men are rather engaged, whom, ayming at <hi>Miters</hi> and a <hi>dominion</hi> over their <hi>fellow-Presbyters,</hi> it much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes to prove the Power of Kings <hi>unlimited,</hi> that ſo they may be able to ſatisfie their <hi>unlimited</hi> deſires, and uphold them in a <hi>boundleſse</hi> juriſdiction over the conſciences of men; but for this Doctor, I know him not, I judge him not.</p>
            <p>Then, for Sedition and Rebellion, The ſearcher of all hearts knowes how farre they were from being the ſcope of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, rather it was an utmoſt aſſay of appeaſment, by ſhewing the way to a diſcreet moderation. Theſe Maſters of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie take a right courſe to ſubvert the Kingdom by diſputing men into a degree of Oppoſition beyond all Attonement, for as I am perſwaded the high ſpirit of Kings will rather incurre the worſt hazzard then ſubmit to ſuch termes, as to be <hi>Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis minores,</hi> that is, ſubject to their Subjects, common ſervants and Officers of their Kingdomes, tyed up to an abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of aſſenting to the Determinations and Votes of the States: So I am as confident, that theſe two Britiſh Nations, yea very many now being in his Majeſties Armies, will ſpend their laſt bloud rather then come downe to this Doctors termes, ſc. <hi>a meere paſſive non reſiſtence</hi> of ſubverſive inſtruments of Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie commands, a ſimple morall liberty, which the baſeſt
<pb facs="tcp:155066:3"/>
ſlaves in the Turks gallies enjoy, becauſe it cannot be taken from them.</p>
            <p>For my part, I doe not reckon my life and liberty worth ſo much pleading for; but the libertie of my Country is deare to me: The eſtabliſhed Government is deare to me, becauſe in it is bound up Religion, the publicke Good, yea the very Title of the King to this Crowne. Theſe I plead for againſt a man, who by his unconſcionable reſolves of Conſcience, hath done what by a pen can be done, to diſſolve them: who in three whole books hath undertaken the Patronage of Subverters of Religion, Laws and Government: and thinks it worth his pains if he can procure them an irreſiſtibilitie.</p>
            <p>I thought I had weighed out Truth to both ſorts with ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a ballance in that Treatiſe, that none had any cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine. But, I ſee, this man muſt have all goe his owne way: He hath a high deſigne, no leſſe then a full conqueſt of all <hi>States;</hi> To bind the Conſciences and hands of Nations, and deliver them up to the Executioner to inflict on them the capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall doom of ſubverſion, if at any time the ſupreme Magiſtrate pleaſe to give the word. To this purpoſe having made ſome animadverſions on ſcattered paſſages of my Book. He is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to publiſh them under the ſtile of a <hi>Reply;</hi> I may well call it a <hi>negative Reply.</hi> He denies what I have aſſerted; and layes downe his owne contradictorie Notions, and that is all; no Scripture nor Reaſon, but what is fully anſwered in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: It is ſo hollow a diſcourſe, that an ordinary eye may ſee through it, without the light of any further Anſwer; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he gives me occaſion of fuller illuſtration, and juſtifying my ſuppoſals; and diſcovering the vanity of his, I have made him this <hi>Return,</hi> in which I have to my knowledge, left unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered no paſſage of moment which concernes me, in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; other parts of it have I left untouched for them to whom they belong.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:155066:4"/>And now with proſtrate humility I beſeech that <hi>ſacred Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> which here againe, is made the matter of this diſpute, not to impute iniquity unto me preſuming, for Truth and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, to make inquiries into it. The Sun-beames ſtrike not dead the poor Mathematician, who ſtanding on this mole-hill, aſſaies by his inſtruments to take the dimenſions of that glorious bodie. Yea the great God of Power permits men without the guilt of ſin, to ſearch into his Perfections, and to ſet, not poſitive, yet negative bounds to Omnipotence it ſelfe. Let not then his Vicegerent be incenſed to diſdain, if we ſearch into the limits of his Power. I envie not it's extent, let it be as large as Truth and Law can ſtretch it: And my dutie binds me to beleeve that he would not have it larger. Princes require a reaſonable ſubjection, and that is beſt performed where the nature and meaſure of Power is beſt knowne: which to find out is all the drift of my former and this Treatiſe, unto which now we will paſſe over.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:155066:4"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſeverall Chapters and Sections.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Caſe miſ-propoſed by the Doctor in his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> His uncharitable raſh Cenſures. His Intents in this Reply come not home to the Caſe in queſtion, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> How far Scripture proofe is to be expected in theſe Caſes, <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2.</label> In the Queſtion of Reſiſtance the Doctors Diſtinction of Times and Perſons is vaine. How farre Reſiſtance is aſserted by me in this and the former Treatiſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3.</label> The Doctor and other of his ſort abuſe Scripture in this Queſtion, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> Scripture warranting this reſiſtance: but having not a word againſt it. The Doctor in words profeſsing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Abſoluteneſſe, but indeed pleading for it, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment not only from God: but ſubordinately from the people, <hi>Sect. 3.</hi> Irreſiſtibleneſſe a Conſequent of Abſoluteneſſe. Limited Monarchie is in the very Power, <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> Mixture muſt be in the very Power. The Doctors ſtrange and ſenceleſſe conceit of Mixture, <hi>Sect. 5.</hi> Conqueſt gives no morall title before conſent, <hi>Sect. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4.</label> The Doctors vaine and falſe ſuppoſals about Gods Ordinance in Soveraignty. It doth not exclude Limitation of
<pb facs="tcp:155066:5"/>
Power, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> His falſe ſuppoſals about the Nature and Quality of Limitation, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> His falſe ſuppoſals about the Cauſes and Meanes of Limitation, <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5.</label> The Soveraignty of this Kingdome Limited in the very Power, and from its firſt Originall. The vanity of the Doctors three Titles by Conquest, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> Arguments for Limitation and Mixture vindicated, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> Seven Queries concerning this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6.</label> The ſtating of the Question of Reſiſtance aſserted. The Appeale <hi>ad conſcientiam generis humani,</hi> in the utmoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention vindicated, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> His arguments againſt Reſervation of Power of Reſiſtance, are anſwered, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 7.</label> The vanity of his conceit about <hi>jus Regis.</hi> His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull citing of <hi>Calvin.</hi> The Government of the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> proved abſolute, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> Inſtances for Reſistance out of the Old Teſtament juſtified, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 8.</label> The Text, <hi>Rom. 13.</hi> nothing concernes this Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. His unjuſt charging of me in this Queſtion. His ſlighting of Doctor <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and other Divines. Reſistance of exceeding Acts, no Reſistance of the Power, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> Emperours of <hi>Rome</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> time proved abſolute, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 9.</label> His nine Reaſons againſt Reſistance anſwered, <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> The five reaſons for Reſiſtance made good, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> The Doctor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes from his firſt Aſſertions, And yeilds us the Queſtion. No evils follow this Reſistance; but many its deniall, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole, <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155066:5"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE Treatiſe of Monarchie. OR, An Anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>FERNES</hi> Reply.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> An Anſwer to the firſt Section of his Reply.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt Section containes his <hi>Preface,</hi> where <hi>p.</hi> 2. He <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> taxes me, <hi>that I looke not with a ſingle eye on what he hath written, miſconſtruing it many times:</hi> but whether I have ſo done or no, it will be manifeſt in the ſequell. Then more then once, he cenſures me for being <hi>engaged.</hi> What engagements I have, appeares before in my <hi>Preface:</hi> But, <hi>I ſet up my rest upon a groundleſſe fancie of ſuch a mixture and conſtitution of this Monarchy, &amp;c.</hi> Whoſe ſuppoſals are groundleſſe fancies, his or mine, I doubt not will fully appeare in this enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Neither had I any other purpoſe to which I have fitted that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155066:6"/>
Treatiſe then the ſimple finding out of truth, God knowes how ever the Doctor pleaſeth to cenſure the purpoſes of my heart, Viewing this Reſolvers diſcourſe, for the ſatisfaction of my conſcience, I found it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and not approaching the Caſe which now troubles the world: Men enquire about the Lawfulneſſe of Reſiſtance of <hi>Inſtruments:</hi> He anſwers concerning Reſiſtance of the <hi>King:</hi> Men demand, Whether Reſiſtance of ſubverſive Inſtruments be the Reſiſtance of Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance forbidden, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. He ſuppoſeth that which is the Queſtion; and makes that the ground of his Reſolve which is the ſole thing at which the conſcience ſcruples. This put me on a Diſcourſe of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, that ſo by a diſtinct conſidering of the grounds of true Policie, I might both ſatisfie my ſelfe and others: and not ſuffer mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, ſeriouſly deſiring found information to be either puzled or miſled by ſo confuſe and indirect a Reſolution. Yet ſomething there is which he likes in me, that is, as much as ſerves his own turne. <hi>I doe with much ingenuity diſclaime, and with no leſſe reaſon confute ſeverall Aſſertions of other writers, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 2. Would he could as well have ſeen my confutation of his, as of other errours: What I have ſaid againſt him, as it proceeds from the ſame impartiall ſpirit, ſo it containes the ſame truth; as, I doubt not, the judicious Reader will diſcerne. But yet <hi>I hold the ground on which their Abſurd aſſertions are raiſed,</hi> ſc. <hi>that the Mixture is in the Supremacie of Power, only I give the King,</hi> apicem poteſtatis, <hi>the top or excellency of Power, that is, the King is the crown or top of the head, &amp;c.</hi> Thus is he pleaſed to jeere me, but how juſtly, it will hereafter appeare. And wheras I place the Authority of determining the laſt controverſies in a mixt Government, not in the two Houſes, this he commends in me: but that I doe not aſcribe it to the King; This he exclaimes againſt, <hi>as a ready way to confuſion,</hi> but why, and how it is ſo, he tells us not; only promiſeth to ſpeake of it <hi>more below,</hi> but where that <hi>below</hi> is, I cannot find.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> After he hath thus touched upon thoſe things which he is pleaſed to tax in my Treatiſe. He proceeds, <hi>p.</hi> 4. to ſhew us what his intent was of firſt undertaking and now proceeding in this Argument. Well: let us heare what it was. <hi>The intent of his firſt Treatiſe was to reſolve the Conſciences of miſled people, touching the unlawfulneſſe of Armes now taken up againſt the King.</hi> He erres in his propoſing of the very Caſe. I believe he knowes no conſcience miſled touching this matter: The Caſe which he ſhould have reſolved, if he had done any thing, was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155066:6"/>
touching the unlawfulneſſe of Armes now taken up againſt ſubverting inſtruments of the Government of the Kingdome; and that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of theſe is a Reſiſting of the King; No wonder if he who ſhootes at a wrong marke looſeth all his arrowes. This wrong propoſing and proſecuting of ſo weighty a caſe (which I doubt was purpoſely done) ſet me firſt on work in this buſineſſe. Heare then the caſe more ſimply propoſed: and I refer me to the conſciences of men, whether I come not neerer the truth of it, then this proponent hath done. The Houſes declare Religion and eſtabliſhed Government to be in apparent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, by meanes of ſome ſubverſive Counſellours and Inſtruments about the King. This being ſuppoſed, they proceed according to <hi>Vote</hi> to the <hi>Ordinance</hi> and execution of the <hi>Militia,</hi> ſo to reſiſt and apprehend thoſe Counſellours and Inſtruments from whom they had declared the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſpring. This put on the Doctor to his firſt booke, to <hi>reſolve</hi> the conſciences of men, that it was unlawfull: Now ſee what courſe he tels us he took to reſolve men in this caſe. He undertakes to make good two Aſſertions. 1. <hi>Were the King ſo ſeduced, it were not ſafe to beare part in the reſiſtance of Armes now uſed againſt him.</hi> 2. <hi>That the caſe is not ſo, as they ſuppoſe, but rather apparently contrary.</hi> In the proofe of theſe two, he ſpends his whole book. Concerning the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I intend no controverſie with the Doctor: Would he could make it cleare to the ſatisfaction of the conſciences of all men; that were the way indeed not only to ſatisfie mens conſciences, but to calme the Kingdome into a bleſſed peace. But the Doctor is but ſlight in that part; and ſayes nothing, but what, as appeares in the Debate in the end of my Treatiſe, may ſoone be anſwered out of the Declarations of the Houſes, and the freſh memory of paſt occurrents: And in this reply he hath not ſo much as touched upon that Chapt. of my book: But that which in his firſt Tract he mainely, and in this Reply he ſolely labours to make good is the firſt <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> which is a univerſall one, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be examined in all Ages and Governments, whatſoever becomes of this preſent contention in this Kingdome. Now concerning that <hi>Theſis,</hi> in my Treatiſe of Monarchy I have affirmed and confirmed two things. 1. That if he could make it good, yet it were nothing to the buſineſſe he hath undertook; which is to ſatisfie the conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Unlawfulneſſe of Reſiſting Inſtruments, not the King, of which hee hath ſpoken very little or nothing at all. 2. That if he could prove that in ſome Kingdomes where the will of the King is the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155066:7"/>
peoples Law, Reſiſtance of Inſtruments were unlawfull, if actuated by the Soveraignes will: Yet in Legall and Limited Governments, it doth not follow to be true: yet this he muſt make good, if in our preſent caſe he ſatisfie mens conſciences as he undertakes. Theſe two are the ſumme of my Anſwer to the Doctor in that Treatiſe, and if in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply he doth any thing, he muſt ſpeake to theſe points. Something he hath here ſpoken concerning the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> in Supremacy, <hi>Of Caſes of Reſiſtance; of Kinds of Monarchy, of the Conſtitution of this Monarchy;</hi> but how truly and ſatisfactorily, it is my part to examine, and let the world judge.</p>
               <p>But as if he had already cleared the matter, he proceeds to give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence before the cauſe be heard: <hi>And doubts not to call the contrary Reſolution a Blaſpheming of God and the King,</hi> p 4. I anſwer, If there be any which will defend the lawfulneſſe of taking Armes againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and in any caſe to <hi>reſiſt the Powers,</hi> They croſſe the evident truth of Scripture, and I condemne them: Yet me thinks the Doctor deales ſomewhat ſeverely with them, to call them <hi>Blaſphemers of God,</hi> for every errour about the word is not <hi>Blaſphemie;</hi> but a wilfull and obſtinate ſpeaking evill of the things of God. Likewiſe concerning a King, if it be true that he be ſeduced; then it is no <hi>blasphemie,</hi> which alwayes is a <hi>falſhood.</hi> If it be falſe, yet it is inhumane to call it a <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming,</hi> when it imputes nothing to him, but <hi>to be ſeduced,</hi> which the beſt and moſt innocent Prince may be; ſure, if it be <hi>a blaſpheming,</hi> it is of the Counſellours and ſeducers, for to them the evill is imputed.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>p.</hi> 6. He comes to ſpeake of what he intends in this preſent booke: <hi>ſc.</hi> that he will cleare this point, <hi>That the Doctrine teaching that ſubjects may take Armes againſt their Soveraigne for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Religion and Liberties, when in danger of ſubverſion, is destitute of Scripture and true reaſon.</hi> As I ſaid, ſtill he drives at a vaine ſcope; to prove that which none denies: Let him prove, that in our Kingdome, Reſiſtance of ſubverſive inſtruments is a taking Armes againſt their Soveraigne, and he does the work; elſe he proves in vaine. But let us ſee how in the <hi>proceſſe of this booke,</hi> that will be cleared which none doth deny. <hi>Firſt upon examination of places of Scripture it will appeare, that Gods people were continually under Kings which they might not reſiſt, &amp;c.</hi> What then? muſt it needs follow, that all other people muſt too? But whether the word containes any thing againſt Reſiſtance, and how far, we ſhall enquire in the proceſſe of this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155066:7"/>
diſpute. <hi>Secondly, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the examination of Reaſon, it will appeare how inconſiſtent ſuch a Power of Reſiſtance in ſubjects is with Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</hi> Indeed he will make appeare a great matter; would he would ſpeake ſomething to the Queſtion, and not proceed ſo indiſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; I hope in the proceſſe of his book he will come neerer to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe then here he promiſeth, or elſe all our labour will be to little purpoſe.</p>
               <p>After he hath told us what great matters we are to expect in his <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> booke; he complaines how much his expectation hath been deceived by his Adverſaries. He confeſſes, They have great <hi>appearance of Reaſon raiſed on</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>grounds or principles; ſo that at first ſight it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unreaſonable that ſubjects ſhould be left without this remedy.</hi> If he ſpeake all this of <hi>Reſiſtance of their ſoveraigne,</hi> ſure it ſeemes not at all <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> but agreeable to all reaſon that ſubjects ſhould be without this remedy: It is directly againſt the word and all ſound reaſon, that a people lifting up a Perſon above themſelves, and by ſacred Covenant giving him a Power above themſelves, ſhould afterward on any pretence aſſume a power of Reſiſting that Perſon and power, and violate their own Covenant and Oath of due ſubjection. But if that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be inveſted with a <hi>limited Power:</hi> and he proceed to acts of meere arbitrarineſſe without the limits of that Power conferred on him: Then it is all the reaſon in the world, that the <hi>Limiting States</hi> ſhould exerciſe an effectuall reſtraining Power by reſiſting inſtruments of ſuch arbitrary and ſubverſive acts, and we have not a ſillable of Scripture contradicting it. But if it ſeemed ſo <hi>unreaſonable</hi> to the Doctor, that ſubjects ſhould be without this remedy; why doth he contradict Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in a buſineſſe within its compaſſe? He tells you, <hi>He found Reaſon preſently checked with that ſaying of our Saviour,</hi> Mat. 10.25. <hi>It is enough for the Diſciple that he be as his Maſter.</hi> And was this all the <hi>check.</hi> your Reaſon had? It is a very weake Reaſon which would yeeld to ſuch a check. What? is every Chriſtian bound for his outward ſtate to be in no better caſe then Chriſt was? If he were pleaſed to be borne under an abſolute Government, to be of low and poore condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth this impoſe a neceſſity on all to be no freer, no richer then he was? A man would think his <hi>Reaſon</hi> were not only <hi>checked,</hi> but <hi>broken,</hi> which ſhould ſo argue. Let it be proved that by the providence of God we are brought forth under ſuch a Governement as <hi>our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> was, then will we hold our ſelves bound by his example, to abide
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155066:8"/>
quietly in that condition we are borne to; but if God, as he hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed to many a richer eſtate then Chriſt was pleaſed to have, ſo hath to us a freer Government; then the Apoſtle adviſeth us <hi>to uſe it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and not to be trifled out of it, by a ſhew of our Maſters example, in a caſe in which it binds no man.</p>
               <p>But in what hath his Adverſaries ſo much deceived his expectation? <hi>He expected expreſſe Scripture, but he finds them altogether fayling; only their faith aad perſwaſion is reſolved into an appearance of reaſon raiſed upon</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>grounds and principles,</hi> p. 6. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hooker</hi> might have taught him that the intent of the Scripture is to deliver us <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda;</hi> but in matters within the compaſſe of Reaſon, it is enough if we have evident reaſon for it, <hi>Scriptura non contradicente:</hi> and I am confident the Scripture hath not a tittle againſt ſuch a Reſiſtence as I doe maintaine; and we have reaſon enough for it. The Scripture was not given to preſcribe <hi>frames of Policie,</hi> which are various according to the diſpoſition of people; Generall Rules there are for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which being obſerved, Particulars, which fall under no ſetled Rule, are left to reaſon and the poſitive Lawes of Nations to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Yet we are not wholy deſtitute of warrant from Scripture, as the Doctor affirmes, but are better furniſhed then he, as it will appeare in the ſequell. If <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> or any elſe have raiſed any doctrines on Ariſtotles grounds which will not conſiſt with Gods Ordinance ſet downe in Scripture concerning Authority, I am not bound to make good other mens exceſſes: This Replier knowes, that as I repudiate his Aſſertions tending to the ruine of all Liberties of States: So I hold it unlawfull to uſe any force againſt the perſon, or Authority of the Supreame, even in the moſt Legall and limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. Therefore he doth me exceeding wrong in the cloſe of his firſt Section, to ſay, <hi>that, I agree with the rest to uſe what force they can againſt ſuch a Monarch for ſuppreſſing of his tyranny, &amp;c.</hi> All I ſay is, <hi>that Force may be uſed;</hi> but neither againſt the <hi>Perſon</hi> nor <hi>Authority of the Monarch,</hi> which in all Governments of that nature are to be held ſacred and inviolate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> An anſwer to the ſecond Section concerning Caſes of Reſiſtence.</head>
               <p>I Could have wiſhed, that if it had pleaſed this Doctor to reply any thing, he would have followed the ſteps of my Treatiſe; but ſith he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155066:8"/>
intends no full returne, but doth only catch at here and there a paſſage, without obſerving any order, I will frame my Anſwer to the courſe of his Reply; and cleare the parcels of my book as I find them aſſaulted in my reading of his. The Title of this Section being <hi>Caſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence,</hi> the firſt part of it is ſpent about ſuch Caſes as are put by the <hi>Divines who plead for Defenſive armes.</hi> At length, <hi>p.</hi> 9, 10. He comes to the alone <hi>Caſe</hi> in which I defend Reſiſtence, in the <hi>p.</hi> 51. of my Tract, where I put the Queſtion of <hi>Perſons miſimployed to ſerve the illegall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive commands of the Prince.</hi> And I affirm in ſuch caſe, and of ſuch Perſons Forceable Reſiſtance to be lawfull by the two Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This I prove by five Arguments, which here the Doctor doth not touch, but referres them to the <hi>p.</hi> 93. of this Reply. Only here he gives us a Magiſteriall determination without any proofe at all. But let us heare his Reſolution upon the caſe. He dares not openly to pronounce it unlawfull: but diſtinguiſhes of <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> as if he would yeeld it lawfull in ſome, but not in others; Certes, if for any, then for <hi>the two Estates;</hi> if any, then <hi>Inſtruments of ſubverſion:</hi> if ſimply <hi>none,</hi> why doth he with ſo great cautele diſtinguiſh. Well, <hi>audiamus diſtinguentem: If by thoſe miſimployed perſons be underſtood the Commanders and Souldiers of the Kings Armies, I cannot ſee (nor any man els, I think) but that the reſiſting of them by a contrary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, is a reſiſting of the King, and unlawfull,</hi> p. 9. I anſwer, I cannot ſee, nor any man elſe, I think, why <hi>Commanders</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> ſhould have a priviledge of ſubverting States and Governments more then other men: Can the Royall Power extend to give them an irreſiſtibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and not to others? Certes, if others may be reſiſted, much rather Commanders and Souldiers, becauſe there is greater danger of ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from them then from others: Their being Commanders and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers makes them more dangerous, but not more priviledged: <hi>But, he nor none elſe can ſee, how ſuch can be reſiſted, but it muſt be a reſisting of the King, and unlawfull.</hi> Perhaps he is miſtaken in others, they may have clearer eyes then he hath: In the <hi>p.</hi> 52. of my Treatiſe, I have made it <hi>luce clarius,</hi> that in a <hi>Legall</hi> Monarchy it is not a Reſiſting of the King. Then he proceedeth to another ſort of men which I hope may be reſiſted. <hi>But if by thoſe miſimployed perſons be underſtood other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of oppreſſion in times of peace, before it come to Armes.</hi> What of theſe, may ſuch be reſiſted? Here he reſolves very cautelouſly and timorouſly, after many words, <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>without prejudice</hi> to other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155066:9"/>
aſſertions of his of other reſiſtance, <hi>He conceives it not unreaſonable to ſay, Firſt, if private men be ſodainely aſſaulted, and life immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently endangered, and no meanes of avoiding by flight, then is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall defence lawfull, for ſuch ſodaine aſſault carries no pretence of authority with it.</hi> What is this to the matter? we enquire not of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting aſſailants carrying no pretence of authority with them; but of ſubverters of Government warranted by the Kings will; and carrying pretence of Authority, though they have none. Secondly, If they come with pretence of Authority, there <hi>may be ſeeking redreſſement above from Authority, but if that may not be had, yet no reſiſtance.</hi> And who then minding to kill or rob, may not make a pretence of Authority, that ſo he may effect his miſchiefe without repugnance? But yet the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor will give us a little more, <hi>The Ministers of Power in each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Houſes of Parliament alſo</hi> (for with him they be equall) <hi>may at firſt ſtay, reſtraine, and commit ſuch miſimployed inſtruments, and ſo repreſent the matter againe to the King.</hi> But is not this to reſiſt them? No; he tells us, <hi>this is not to reſist.</hi> No? if miſimployed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments may be <hi>staid, reſtrained, and impriſoned,</hi> ſure they may be reſiſted: Elſe what if they ſhould chooſe, and will not be committed; The Parliament muſt not lay hands on them to compell them; for ſo there may chance to be fight, and ſlaughter in the apprehenſion; and then the Doctor would call it Reſiſtance I think. But ſuppoſe the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament doe commit ſuch perſons and repreſent the matter to the King, <hi>and a King ſhould be ſo obſtinate as to perſiſt in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of thoſe illegall courſes, and to that end imploy the Militia, it is neither Legall nor Reaſonable, they ſhould purſue the oppoſition to the ſetting up of a contrary Militia or Power,</hi> p. 11. Here we ſee the upſhot of the Engliſh freedome, and priviledge of Parliament. This is that which I ſaid; <hi>Thoſe men overturne all liberties, The reſult of their doctrine deſtroyes all policies, reducing them all to that which is arbitrary:</hi> If the King ſhould ſet Souldiers to deſtroy Lawes and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, They may (if they be able) ſtay their hands till they goe to the King, and know whether it be indeed his will and pleaſure to have them deſtroyed or no; If he ſay, Yea; then they muſt returne and ſubmit to the vileſt inſtruments of ſubverſion, and not lift up a hand to reſiſt them. But let us ſee, on what weighty reaſon the Doctor builds this fatall Reſolution. <hi>This were a conteſtation of Power with him whoſe Miniſters they are, a levying of warre, an oppoſing of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155066:9"/>
Armies against Armies.</hi> Sure this man doth much abhorre a Civill Warre: I cannot blame him: but yet we may buy an immunity too deare, at the prize of a ſubverſion of Religion, Laws and Government, which is the caſe in diſpute. This were to chooſe to be killed, rather then to ſight: To have a State ſubverted, rather then diſturbed by a warre to prevent it. I grant, <hi>There muſt be no conteſtation of Power with him whoſe Miniſters they are:</hi> But this is the point to be proved, that in this caſe, it is ſo: I utterly denie the Royall Power in our State can be communicated to ſubverting Inſtruments: And I doe in vaine expect, while the Doctor prooves that, which every where he ſuppoſeth: For he builds all on this foundation, ſc. <hi>That Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is an Abſolute unlimited Power, investing the whole will of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame, and cannot be determined in the exerciſe, but onely morally;</hi> the vanitie of which conceit will appeare hereafter, yet note here in the cloſe, that while he pretends a deteſtation of Civill Warre, he could doe nothing more to foment it, then by defending ſuch Poſitions of intolerable ſervitude: Did not ſuch rigid Counſellours of the King of Iſrael cauſe the greateſt Rent and Civill Warre that ever was made in any Kingdome?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> An Anſwer to the third Section which concerns ſeverall kinds of Monarchy.</head>
               <p>IN my opinion it had been fitter to have treated firſt of <hi>ſeverall kinds <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> of Monarchy;</hi> and then of <hi>Caſes of Reſiſtance;</hi> for the ſubject <hi>in which</hi> ſhould precede the Queſtion <hi>whereof,</hi> in all methodicall proceeding. Here againe in the firſt place, this Replier would make his Reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that penury of Scripture-proofe put me upon diſtinguiſhing of ſeverall kinds of Monarchy, <hi>That ſo I might lay all the defence of Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon Reaſon drawne from the ſeverall condition of Monarchies,</hi> p. 11. I have ſufficiently before diſcovered my intention in that Treatiſe. The Reſiſtence which I defend hath as much proofe from Scripture, as a matter of that nature need to have. Then he abuſes me, as finding fault with Divines, that pleading for abſoluteneſſe of Monarchicall Power in this Kingdome bring proofes from places of Scripture, <hi>p.</hi> 12. I complaine not of <hi>all</hi> Divines, but <hi>ſome,</hi> ſuch as this <hi>Reſolver</hi> is: <hi>Some,</hi> and that but of late yeares; and that but <hi>in this kingdome,</hi> where ſuch doctrines are the rode to preferments: nor doe I blame them <hi>for bringing proofes for ſubjection, and against Reſiſtance from places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155066:10"/>
as he calumniates me; but I blame their groſſe perverting of Scripture; bringing prohibitions of <hi>Reſistance of Powers</hi> againſt them who condemne it as much as themſelves; And of <hi>violating the Lords annointed</hi> againſt them who hold them as ſacred and inviolate, yea on more ſolid grounds then themſelves doe. And their fraudulent reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from one kind of government to another, as if all Politicall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of States for their Liberties did make no variation in the caſe; but that ſtill they were in the ſame State, as the people ſubject to the moſt abſolute vaſſallage.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> But becauſe he boaſts ſo much of <hi>ſetling mens Conſciences on warrant from Scripture, that he expects command or allowance of Reſiſtance from Scripture,</hi> p. 6. <hi>That his Adverſaries reſolve all their faith and perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on an appearance of Reaſon drawne from</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>grounds,</hi> ib. and here <hi>that I obſerve there is but little pretence from Scripture for Reſistance;</hi> and thus would perſwade men, as if he had all Scripture for him; we no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a few huskes of reaſon for us: Let him not thinke to carry it thus away with vaunts and big words: I will profeſſe here once for all. He hath not a ſillable of Scripture or right reaſon to ſatisfie the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with in this controverſie: If it pleaſe this Doctor, let us joyne iſſue upon it, and put the whole caſe on this point. The Queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us is, <hi>Whether in a limited Monarchie, Reſiſtance of ſubverſive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments be unlawfull.</hi> He affirmes, I denie. He undertakes to ſatisfie mens conſciences that it is unlawfull: bringing not one Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſpeakes to the point: Something he brings to proove it <hi>unlawfull to reſiſt the Ordinance of God:</hi> that <hi>the Magistrate which is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame under God is above all Reſiſtance,</hi> p. 84. He doth great matters; who doubts of theſe things: Then <hi>p.</hi> 84. he accumulates nine Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but all ſo <hi>non concluding,</hi> that nineſcore of them will not make one ſound proving Reaſon of the point in queſtion, as it will appeare when we come to conſider them. On the other ſide we have <hi>both</hi> to ſettle mens conſciences on. 1. Examples of Scripture, <hi>ſc.</hi> The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples reſcue of <hi>Jonathan: Davids</hi> armie againſt the cut-throats of <hi>Saul,</hi> that is, ſubverſive Inſtruments: Theſe being particular men, and in an abſolute Monarchie proove the point the more ſtrongly, ſo ſtrongly that the Doctor is faine to flie to that <hi>ordinary</hi> evaſion, of an <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie priviledge.</hi> Beſides all thoſe places which prove it lawfull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt private men, ſeeking to ſubvert Lawes and Religion, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good; ſith in a limited State they are but private men, though
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155066:10"/>
backed with a Commiſſion from the Kings will and pleaſure. 2. Then for Reaſon; I have ſet downe five, <hi>p.</hi> 53. all unanſwerably concluding the point in Queſtion, as I doubt not the conſiderate Reader will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge.</p>
               <p>He profeſſes, p. 12. <hi>That it was never his intent to plead for abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Power in the King, if by abſoluteneſſe of Power be meant a Power of Arbitrary Command.</hi> What his intent is I know not, but he hath fully done the thing, or I have no underſtanding to ſee when a thing is done. In the precedent Section, he reſolves all caſes into the <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium Regis,</hi> the meere pleaſure of the King: allowing the Houſes of Parliament only a power of ſtaying the hands of deſtroyers, till it be expreſſely knowne whether it be the Kings <hi>pleaſure</hi> they ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: And I am confident the meaneſt apprehenſion will diſcerne, that they who make the Monarchs ſole Will the laſt judge of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies: and ſimply deny in the laſt caſe of ſubverſion, all Power of Reſiſtance of Inſtruments, even to the ſupreame Courts of Law and juſtice, doe without any controverſie, reſolve all government into an Arbitrarie Abſoluteneſſe. He adds, <hi>We allow a diſtinction of Monarchies and admit the Government of Kingdomes to be of divers kinds, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a legall reſtraint upon the Power of the Monarch in this Kingdome. Verba datis, rem negatis;</hi> you allow indeed a kind of <hi>diſtinction of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies,</hi> but all within the compaſſe of <hi>Abſolute: A legall reſtraint</hi> you ſeeme to acknowledge; but ſuch an one as reſolves into the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Will of the Monarch, as I have made it appeare in my former Treatiſe; and you will never be able to wipe off by this, or any other Reply. Then he promiſes that in this Booke certaine points <hi>will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be truth, agreeable to Scripture and Reaſon:</hi> ſc. <hi>That Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not the invention of man, but the inſtitution of God: That Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours have their Power not from the people, but from God: That Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Power is one and the ſame in all ſupreames, and can only be limited in the exerciſe. And that where a Prince ſtands ſupreme, and next to God above all the people, there the Subiects may not take armes and make forcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſiſtance for any exorbitances.</hi> Theſe ſeverall Propoſitions how farre they contain Truth, and how far not, I ſhall in the ſequell make appear.</p>
               <p>After theſe great promiſes, he proceeds, <hi>p.</hi> 13. to ſpeake ſomewhat of the <hi>Originall</hi> of Governing Power: and accuſeth me as if <hi>I ſeemed to <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> affirme it to be from God; but in the proceſſe of my booke, he finds me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving it indeed from the people.</hi> I perceiving two contrary opinions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155066:11"/>
concerning the Originall of Government, did in that Treatiſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to reconcile them, and to ſhew in what ſence both are true. To that end, as there is manifeſt, <hi>p</hi> 4. I diſtinguiſhed 3 things. <hi rend="sup">1</hi> It's <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi> It's <hi>Limitation</hi> to one kind. <hi rend="sup">3</hi> It's <hi>determination</hi> to one indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall Perſon and Family. The firſt of theſe I did affirme to be <hi>from God:</hi> The two latter <hi>from Men,</hi> and then concluded, <hi>In theſe things we have Doctour Fernes conſent.</hi> Let us ſee what exceptions he can take at this peaceable aſſay of Reconcilement. <hi>In the proceſſe of my Diſcourſe he findes me deriving it from the people.</hi> What then? Doe I denie it thereby to be from God? as if <hi>Subordinates did exclude one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi> God hath ordained that Powers ſhould <hi>be:</hi> People by vertue of that Ordinance give them <hi>exiſtence</hi> in this or that <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>ſubiect.</hi> The Doctor acknowledges all this, but <hi>not in my ſence,</hi> p. 14. He grants the <hi>Deſignation of the Perſon, and the Limitation of the Power to ſeverall kinds to be from the conſent of the People.</hi> I ſay no more; why doe we not then agree? The plaine truth is, The Doctor will not have <hi>Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Power</hi> to be at all from the people, what ever he pretends: How then the Limitation of the Power to ſeverall kinds is from the people, as the Doctor yeelds, I cannot tell. Is not Limitation of it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to kinds, Limitation of the Power it ſelfe? But he is poſſeſſed that <hi>my ſound ſence is another ſence from his;</hi> what other he doth not ſhew: but it is another which he likes not. Why? <hi>Becauſe ſometimes I ſay, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple reſerve a Power to oppoſe or diſplace the Magiſtrate: Sometime they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt themſelves of all ſuperiority.</hi> 'Tis true, I ſay ſo, but withall I ſay, that when they reſerve ſuch a Power, they conſtitute no Monarchy. Is it not ſo, in the higheſt Miniſters of Power in Ariſtocracies and Democracies? What can he ſay againſt ſo apparent a Truth? 2. <hi>I call them,</hi> p. 63. <hi>Architectonicall</hi> Powers. This he derides and ſaies, <hi>This is the riddle of this Governing Power originally in the people. They are Architectonicall Powers, but build upon foundations laid in the aire,</hi> p. 14, Then he gives his reaſon, <hi>For before Government eſtabliſhed they have not any politique Power, whereby a Command may be laid upon others, but only a naturall power of private reſistance.</hi> This is falſe, that they have <hi>onely</hi> a naturall power of private Reſiſtance. They have indeed no <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall</hi> politique power, for we ſpeake of a people free from all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but they have a <hi>virtuall radicall power,</hi> by publike conſent and contract to conſtitute this or that forme of Government, and reſigne up themſelves to a condition of ſubjection on <hi>Termes</hi> and after a <hi>form</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:155066:11"/>
of their owne conſtitution; ſo the <hi>Athenians, Lacedemonians</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> of old having expelled their Kings: and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> with others of latter times have done: This is that which I called <hi>Architect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onicall Power;</hi> and the Replier vainly carpes at the name, when he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not denie the thing. But I know what he aimes at in all this, <hi>ſc.</hi> That Gods Ordinance is an abſolute boundleſſe Power in all Supremes, unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any limitation, but in the exerciſe. Of which fully afterwards.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label>
               </p>
               <p>At length <hi>He takes a nearer view of the Formes of Monarchie, ſpoken of by me, and makes a few obſervations upon ſuch particulars at him plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,</hi> p. 14. Let us follow his ſteps. Firſt, for Abſolute Monarchie, whereas I ſay it is, <hi>when Soveraignty is ſo fully in one, that it hath no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation under God, but the Monarches owne will.</hi> He approoves my deſcription; but threatens <hi>to remember it below,</hi> p. 15. Let him doe ſo; and make his beſt advantage of it, only here he cannot forbeare one note, that then it is not the deniall of reſiſtance which makes a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch abſolute; but the deniall of a law to bound his Will. I doe grant it; but with all I ſay, that it is <hi>neceſſariò conſequutivum,</hi> though it be not <hi>conſtitutivum:</hi> for ſith a Monarch which is obſolute hath no Law to bound his Will; but his very Will is the Subjects Law, then every act of his Will is Gods Ordinance, and ſo by conſequence it is unreſiſtible. Alſo, <hi>p.</hi> 15. He allowes it, when I ſay, <hi>A limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch is he who hath a Law beſides his owne Will for the meaſure of his power.</hi> But yet he diſlikes that I ſay, <hi>He muſt be limited in the Power it ſelfe, and not only in the exerciſe;</hi> and I added a reaſon, <hi>for an Abſolute Monarch may ſtint himſelfe in the exerciſe of his Power, and yet remaine abſolute.</hi> What ſaies he to this? <hi>True, if ſuch a Monarch limit himſelf and reſerve a Power to vary,—but if he fix a Law with promiſe not to varie, then in thoſe caſes he is limited.</hi> Note the fraud of this <hi>Replier,</hi> he alters his terms and puts things as oppoſite which are not ſo: He ſhould ſay, if be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe, and <hi>reſerve a power to varie;</hi> then he is abſolute; but if he limit himſelfe and <hi>reſerve no Power to varie</hi> (for then the oppoſition is direct) then he is limited. But in ſtead of ſaying <hi>(and reſerve no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to varie)</hi> he ſaies, but <hi>[if he promiſe not to vary]</hi> I ſay that <hi>promiſe not to vary,</hi> if it be a <hi>ſimple promiſe</hi> of not varying, it doth not make him limited in his Power, any more then <hi>morally,</hi> and ſo every Abſolute Monarch is limited. I affirme ſtill, it is Limitation of the <hi>Power it ſelfe,</hi> not barely of the <hi>exerciſe,</hi> which conſtitutes a Limited Monarch: for Monarchy is a ſtate of Power, and therefore it's <hi>ſpecificative</hi> diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155066:12"/>
muſt be from ſomething which diſtinguiſheth Powers, and not the exerciſe of Powers; but this is enough proved in the 5<hi rend="sup">t</hi> page of that Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he blames me for that <hi>I ſuppoſe a Limited Monarch muſt be radically, that is, originally inveſted with ſuch a meaſure of limited Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and that limited,</hi> ab externo, <hi>and not from the free determination of his owne Will.</hi> Here he adds <hi>originally</hi> of his owne; that ſo he might ſeeme to finde a contradiction, when I afterward ſay, that it may be done by <hi>originall conſtitution,</hi> or by <hi>after condeſcent;</hi> but yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>I have a ſalve, when I make it ſuch a condeſcent, as is equivalent to an Originall Conſtitution, becauſe amounting to a change of Title, and a reſolution in the Monarch to be ſubjected to, no other way.</hi> I make no <hi>ſalve,</hi> nor doe I need any; he who weighes the Uniformity of Truth in that Treatiſe will ſee it needs no ſalves: Onely I diſtinguiſh thoſe things which are in their natures diſtinct, which if the Doctour had done, this Contention either had not been begun, or would ſoon have an end: Who ſees not that a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> whereby a Monarch may bind himſelfe may either be with a <hi>limitation</hi> of the bond of ſubjection, or <hi>without:</hi> And that this makes a reall difference: for <hi>in this</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment remaines the ſame, becauſe the Dutie of ſubjection received no variation; but <hi>in that</hi> there is for ſo much a <hi>Tranſitus</hi> into a limited condition. But theſe things cannot be more fully and clearly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then they are in the page 13. of that Treatiſe. But he anſwers, <hi>Where there is ſuch a change of Title, it is done at once, and by expreſſe and notorious reſignation of former Power; but it is not neceſſary that an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarch ſhould come to a limited Condition after that manner.</hi> I ſay, if he will paſſe into a limited condition, it is neceſſary there be a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Power, elſe he is not truly limited: But that all ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation be done <hi>at once and by notorious reſignation,</hi> it is not neceſſary, as will appeare afterward where this matter of <hi>Limitation</hi> is more diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inctly handled.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label> His next complaint is againſt ſomething I have in the page 25. <hi>ſc.</hi> That in a mixed Government (if it be of three) the Soveraign Power muſt be in all three originally, and from fundamentall conſtitution. <hi>He judges this not neceſſary, p.</hi> 17. and he gives a wonderfull Reaſon: For as <hi>Limitation may be only of the exerciſe of the Power, and not of the Power it ſelfe; ſo mixture is in regard of Perſons ioyned to the Monarch for certain acts and purpoſes; but that they ſhould have any ſhare in the Soveraign power,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155066:12"/>
the nature of Monarchy will not admit.</hi> 1. Juſt ſo; for as a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is not limited unleſſe there be a limitation of Power, for Monarchy is a Power; ſo a Monarchy cannot be mixed, unleſſe there be a mixture of Powers, for Monarchy is a Power; and to ſay a mixt Monarchy, and yet the Power not mixt, is to ſpeake contradictories. 2. If the mixture be not of divers concurrent Powers; wherof is it? He tells us, <hi>of the Monarch and certaine other Perſons joyned with him for certaine acts and purpoſes.</hi> Theſe joyned Perſons, have they any concurring Power to doe thoſe acts for which they are joyned? If not; then the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning is futulous and vaine, and the Power of Monarchy is mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a Perſon having Power, and of others having no Power to doe that for which they are joyned. You will ſay, They have Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but not diſtinct from that of the Monarch: that is, they have none; for in mixture, if it be not diſtinct, it is none at all. Againe if they have any, it muſt be diſtinct, for ſubordinate it cannot be; if the Acts to which they concurre be ſupreme Acts, unleſſe we ſhould be ſo abſurd as to ſay, They may concurre to ſupreme Acts, by a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Power. But let us ſee, what a maine Reaſon he hath for aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a conceit ſubject to ſuch abſurdities. <hi>Such a mixture would make ſeverall independent powers in the ſame State or Kingdome, which is moſt abſurd.</hi> I grant it is abſurd, if he ſpeake of ſeverall <hi>complete</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent powers; but to affirme ſeverall <hi>incomplete</hi> independent powers concurring to make up one <hi>integrall</hi> mixt power, it is no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity at all for ſo it is, in all <hi>Ariſtocracies</hi> and <hi>Democracies,</hi> and muſt be acknowledged in all <hi>mixed</hi> States, where the ſupremacie is not wholy in the hands of one perſon. Yet here we doe not ſo make them <hi>independent,</hi> but that we give a large predominancie to One, as, <hi>in nature,</hi> in all mixed bodies there is, as I have at large explained my ſelfe in the next Section, if the Doctor had been at leaſure to have taken notice of it. I yeild to that which he ſayes, <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>that it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the Mixture ſhould be ſo Originall, but that it may alſo come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by condeſcent:</hi> It matters not, ſo it be originall, that is, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall:</hi> of <hi>Powers,</hi> and not of <hi>meere Acts:</hi> And indeed, there cannot be a mixture of <hi>Acts,</hi> unleſſe it be alſo of <hi>Powers:</hi> for <hi>Acts</hi> are from <hi>Powers:</hi> and where <hi>Powers</hi> are ſubordinate, there can be no mixture in their <hi>Acts;</hi> the Acts of cauſes ſubordinate, are alſo ſubordinate, and not coordinate and mixed. But I there brought two Arguments to prove that <hi>in a Mixed Government, the Concurrents muſt have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155066:13"/>
and diſtinct Powers.</hi> Let us ſee how he anſwers them. 1. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe elſe it would be no mixture, but a derivation of Power, which is ſeen in the moſt ſimple Monarchy.</hi> He anſwers, that <hi>derivation</hi> of Power is either upon <hi>ſubſtitute Officers</hi> ſupplying the abſence of the Monarch in the execution of Power: and this is in the moſt ſimple Monarchy. Or elſe <hi>upon Perſons whoſe concurrence and conſent is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to certaine Acts of Monarchicall Power; and this makes a mixture, though they have no ſhare in the Power it ſelfe,</hi> p. 17. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, 1. Abſence or preſence of the Monarch; whether they Act for him, or with him, varies not the caſe, If the Power they work by be derived from him, then it is his Power, and ſo conſtitutes no Mixture. 2. As if in the moſt ſimple Monarchy, the Soveraigne doth mannage the <hi>ardua imperij,</hi> the weightieſt matters of State alone; and not by conſent of his Counſell; without whom he is <hi>morally</hi> bound, (that is, on the ſinne of raſhneſſe) not to tranſact them, and that is all, which the Doctor yeilds to the Houſes of Parliament, <hi>ſc.</hi> that the King is <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> bound to their concurrence and conſent in <hi>certaine Acts.</hi> This is nothing but the ſhadow of a Mixture; If the Power of Acting be ſo in one, that, if he pleaſe, he may doe thoſe Acts without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of thoſe adjunct Perſons, though he ought not, it is no Mixture, becauſe the Power is ſimple and One; and mixed Acts cannot flow from one ſimple Power. This the Doctor ſees, and therefore ſayes, <hi>If this Authour will not call this a Mixture, we cannot help it,</hi> p. 18. We doe not enquire of <hi>Names,</hi> but of <hi>things;</hi> nor whether it make a difference in Government or no; We treat of a <hi>Mixt Governement:</hi> and, I think, no man of common ſenſe will affirme, that a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be really mixed, and yet the Power be ſimple. 2. <hi>Becauſe the End of Mixture (which is Effectuall Limitation) cannot be had by a derivate Power.</hi> He anſwers; <hi>Though a Derivate Power cannot ſet new bounds to the Soveraigne Power, yet may it ſtand to keep in a legall way thoſe bounds which the ſoveraigne Power hath ſet to it ſelfe.</hi> Obſerve, He dares not to ſay, They <hi>may keep:</hi> but only <hi>ſtand to keep;</hi> nor <hi>ſtand</hi> neither, but by <hi>advice;</hi> that is <hi>morally:</hi> If he will exceed thoſe bounds, the Act is valid, and hath all its Authority without them: Only he ſins, if he doe ſo; becauſe he hath promiſed he would not doe it without them: Here's excellent Limitation and Confinement from exorbitancies: A bare <hi>promiſe,</hi> without ſuch adoe, in conſtituting <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Mixtures,</hi> would be altogether as good a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155066:13"/>
bounds; but of this we ſhall have more occaſion to ſpeake afterward.</p>
               <p>In the cloſe of this Section he turnes back to the <hi>p.</hi> 21. of my book,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> and hath ſomewhat to ſay to my Aſſertions about Monarchy by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. There firſt I ſay, <hi>If the invaſion be made upon pretence of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and the pretender doth prevaile, it is not Conquest properly, but a Vindication of a Title: and then the Government is ſuch as the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is by which he claimed.</hi> He tells us, <hi>He ſees no injuſtice in it, if ſuch a one having prevailed ſhould uſe ſuch a people as a Conquerour,</hi> p. 19. The Lord keep us from this mans juſtice. What; No injuſtice? If the Pretenders Title allowed by a great part of the people, he by their aide ſubdues the reſt, ſhall he for their labour cruſh them into ſervitude, and uſe the power of a Conquerour, without injuſtice? 2. Suppoſe the people not convinced of the right of his Title make at firſt ſome op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; but yet the pretence of his Title, and apprehenſion that he ſeekes no more power then his Title imports, work a yeilding diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in them, ſo that they withſtand not ſo univerſally, nor ſo long as they might have done; but at length ſubmit to him on his pretended termes: were it not high injuſtice to take advantage on ſuch a people, and having them under hatches to deſert thoſe termes on which they yeilded, and uſe the full right of a Conquerour: This was Englands caſe with Duke <hi>William.</hi> But the maine thing which ſticks by him is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I have delivered, p. 23. <hi>It is an uncontrolable truth in policie, that the conſent of the people, either by themſelves or their Anceſtours, is the only meane in ordinary providence, by which ſoveraignty is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon any perſon or family.</hi> Againſt this he is very angry; and oppoſeth it in many words; but to my Argument from the Morall bond of ſubjection, he ſayes nothing at all. He termes it <hi>good policie, but bad divinity,</hi> p. 20. And ſets up an <hi>Antipoſition,</hi> that <hi>when the invading Prince has perfectly ſubdued a people (there being no heyre to whom they are bound) and hath ſetled and conſtituted a frame of Government, then providence doth ſufficiently diſcover it ſelfe, and ſuch a people ought to ſubmit and take this Prince as ſet over them by the hand of providence.</hi> As if theſe two were contrary: I ſay, <hi>They are not bound untill they conſent:</hi> He ſayes, in ſuch a caſe <hi>they are bound to conſent,</hi> becauſe then providence diſcovers it ſelfe: And he brings <hi>Calvin</hi> at large to prove that which none denies: I grant a people (not preobliged,) fully overcome ſhould much ſin againſt Gods <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> by obſtinacie, if on a meere will, they conſent not to reaſonable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155066:14"/>
termes of ſubjection: But this I ſay, There is no morall obligation to Authority, before that conſent bind them: Conqueſt may be an <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent cauſe;</hi> but the <hi>immediate and formall cauſe</hi> is only the conſent of the people; which he cannot ſay againſt; for that muſt be <hi>morall,</hi> and not meerely <hi>violent.</hi> The call of providence challengeth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented ſubmiſſion, if there be no reaſon hindring it; but if a precedent Oath or ſome other ſound reaſon intervene, then it is no call requiring ſubmiſſion: Neither can the fulleſt conqueſt make a people debtors, but they remaine free from any morall bond; for the providence of God being of it ſelfe externall, can induce no morall ſtate; but that providence which on one diſcovery calls to a ſubmiſſion: on a like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery may free them againe, if nothing elſe come between, to render them morally bound: A Travellour, by the providence of God ſhut up into the hands of a Robber, hath his life and protection promiſed him in his journey, if he will promiſe to pay him ſo much money: I ſay, this Travailor ſhould ſin againſt his own life, and the providence of God, offering him thoſe termes, if obſtinately he refuſe ſubmiſſion: Yet no man will ſay he owes the robber ſo much money, becauſe he hath him at his mercy, untill he by promiſe make himſelfe a debtor: Thus have I made good that <hi>maxime</hi> of mine to be <hi>an uncontrouleable Truth, good Policie, and good Divinity too;</hi> maugre all the Doctor hath or can ſay againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Wherein the vanity and falſhood of the ſuppoſals whereon the Doctor hath built all his diſcourſes is made appeare.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> AFter a ſcattered gleaning of paſſages in the former Sections, the Doctor undertakes the two great Queſtions. 1. Of the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of this Monarchy, in his Sect. 4. 2. Of <hi>Reſiſtence,</hi> in the remainder of his book. Which two, we ſhould now immediately purſue; but that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other work more conducent to the ending of this contention will for a while divert me.</p>
               <p>Errour in the ſearch of controverted truths doth more often ariſe from the <hi>judgement,</hi> then from the <hi>reaſon:</hi> Men doe more offend in laying falſe grounds; then in deducing falſe inferences from true grounds; This I have obſerved in the Doctors bookes: He truly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, but from falſe principles; and then the ſuperſtructure muſt needs be anſwerable, ſo that, overthrow his foundations, and then all his buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155066:14"/>
will of it ſelfe ruine into apparent falſhood. I confeſſe he every where ſayes the ſame of my Grounds, on which I have built that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: He cals them <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>groundleſſe ſuppoſals,</hi> and <hi>fancies,</hi> and what elſe he pleaſeth: I will therefore make him a fayre offer: Let us make a ſhort work of it: let us joyne iſſue upon our <hi>ſuppoſals,</hi> on which both our diſcourſes are built.</p>
               <p>This Doctors <hi>ſuppoſals</hi> which he ſcarce ever makes ſhew to prove and on which he hath built his <hi>Reſolves</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> I doubt not to call <hi>unſound</hi> and <hi>falſe:</hi> and doe profeſſe the contrary to be my grounds whoſe truth I will maintaine. His may be reduced to foure heads. 1. Concerning the <hi>Ordinance of God in Soveraignty.</hi> 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Quality</hi> of <hi>Limitation.</hi> 3. The <hi>Meanes and cauſes of Limitation.</hi> 4. The <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of this Monarchy. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this order we will take them into examination.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Of the <hi>Ordinance of God in Magiſtracy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of Gods ordinance in ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie.</note> He proceeds on two falſe principles. 1. That <hi>the Governing power is one and the ſame which God gives and ſettles upon the perſon that is ſupreme,</hi> p. 13. that is, it is abſolute and unlimited in the power it ſelfe; and may be limited on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the exerciſe thereof, <hi>p.</hi> 17. 2. Which followes from the former, that <hi>Conſent of people may be the meane of deſigning the perſon, and yeilding ſubjection to him, who elſe could not challenge it more then an other man; alſo a meane of limiting that power in the exerciſe of it; but not the meaſure of the power it ſelfe, which in ſuch a meaſure is given of God to all Soveraignes,</hi> p. 41. ſo then;<note place="margin">Queſtion propoſed.</note> let this be the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Whether it be Gods Ordinance that Governing power in all So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignes be one unlimited thing; and can receive no meaſure from the people?</hi> The Doctor affirmes it; and <hi>p.</hi> 84, tells us he hath <hi>often inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated</hi> it; but he ſhould once directly prove it, if he be able, ſo he might have preſcribed to the whole controverſie; for if he can make this good, in vaine doe we enquire about the <hi>conſtitution</hi> of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; or the lawfulneſſe of <hi>reſiſtance</hi> of ſubverſive inſtruments of the Princes will. Doth he think a covert <hi>inſinuation</hi> would ſerve the turne to impoſe ſuch an Aſſertion, which fruſtrates the intent of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in framing limitations of Governing power; and captives all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an abſolute <hi>paſſive ſubjection</hi> to the vileſt inſtruments of the will of him who is ſupreme. In all his <hi>reply</hi> I find but two places which have any ſhew of proofe of this overbold Aſſertion. One is p. 14. <hi>Before Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed the people have not any power of a community
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155066:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:155066:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:155066:16"/>
or politick power whereby a command may be laid upon others; but only a naturall power of private reſiſtance.</hi> The other is p. 42. <hi>The people have not of themſelves out of Government, the maine power, the power of life and death, how then can they give it either for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or reſerve it for Reſistance?</hi> Here be weake foundations to build ſuch an Aſſertion, and three ſuch inſulting books on. What a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing this is, I ſhall make appeare anon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Queſtion ſtated.</note>Now I hold the <hi>Negative</hi> of this Queſtion; and doubt not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it firme truth: To that end, firſt I will premiſe ſuch things as we agree in, that ſo the point in queſtion may the more diſtinctly appeare. Which I apprehend are or may be theſe. 1. <hi>That Governing power is originally from Gods Ordinance.</hi> 2. <hi>That it being ſo, is unreſistible in its whole latitude, in all the acts which flow from it.</hi> This the Apoſtle is cleare for, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and for no more, that I know. Alſo that this is true as well in Limited as Abſolute Governments; <hi>v. g.</hi> In abſolute Monarchy, where Authority doth inveſt the <hi>whole will;</hi> the Monarch is unreſiſtible in all the acts of his reaſonable <hi>will;</hi> becauſe all are acts flowing from Gods Ordinance. So in limited Monarchy, where Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity doth not ſimply inveſt the <hi>will</hi> of a Monarch, but ſo far forth as it is regulated by ſuch a law, the Monarch is unreſiſtible in all the acts of his will which are according to that law; becauſe they are acts flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Gods Ordinance: Yea though either of theſe doe limit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of his power, no way thereby diminiſhing the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his power; and afterward exceed thoſe limits, yet he is unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible, and to be ſubjected to <hi>actively</hi> in lawfull things, and <hi>paſſively</hi> in unlawfull: my reaſon is, becauſe even thoſe acts, notwithſtanding limitation, flow from Gods Ordinance of Authority, which remaines the ſame, and not leſſened by ſuch limitation. 3. <hi>This governing power is ordinarily conveyed to perſons by publick conſent,</hi> which is a point made good in my former Treatiſe, and in the former chapter hereof. 4. <hi>That this publick conſent is not only a meane, but hath a cauſall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence in conveying Authority to perſons.</hi> 5. <hi>That men working by ſuch conſent as ſecond cauſes, doe neceſſarily convey ſuch Authority, as God hath ordained;</hi> ſo that, if it can be proved either by Scripture or ſound reaſon, that it is Gods ordinance, that ſupremacie ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited, and as large as all the acts of his will which hath it, then what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever men capitulate about limitation of it, is vaine, ſo that the Doctor need prove only that point; and for my part I will give him the cauſe.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155066:16"/>
6. <hi>Limitation of Power may be either of Acts,</hi> when Power is convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Perſons to doe certaine Acts of Power; but not all. Or elſe of <hi>Manner of working;</hi> when Power is conveyed to doe all Acts of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but according to ſuch a preſcribed Rule. Now I grant the former cannot be in the conveyance of Soveraigne Power, an inferiour Officer may be limited by commiſſion to certaine acts of Power; and have no Authority to do other Acts of power; but when Soveraignty is conveyed, and the Perſon is ſet up <hi>next to God, above all the people,</hi> as the Doctour ſaith. He muſt have an unlimited Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in reſpect of Acts of Government: for Gods Ordinance is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that there ſhould be <hi>Power</hi> for ſuch an end; ſc. a <hi>Peaceable life in godlineſſe and honeſtie;</hi> but <hi>ſufficiencie of Power</hi> for the attainment of that end: So that all Power of doing any Act needfull for that end, muſt be in him who is ſupreme, and the comprehenſive Head of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to inferiour Magiſtrates. So that all the Queſtion truly ſtated is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the other ſort of Limitation, ſc. <hi>Whether Soveraigne Power be ſo unlimited in its Rule of Acting, that it inveſteth the whole Reaſonable Will of him who hath it:</hi> So that all the acts which proceed from him who hath it according to the rule of his owne Reaſon, be <hi>potestative,</hi> and from Gods Ordinance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, having thus punctually ſtated the Queſtion,<note place="margin">Queſtion determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation muſt proceed in a double way, ſc. 1. <hi>In ſimple Governments.</hi> 2. <hi>In mixed Governments.</hi> I do maintain the <hi>Negative</hi> in both: and my proof ſhall be formed accordingly.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, <hi>In ſimple Government, Power is not one <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited thing <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>1</label> in the ſupreme:</hi> But may be limited in the very being and root of it. 1. The cauſe or meane by which alone it is conveyed, if it beſtow or <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> convey only a limited Power, then it is limited in the very <hi>Being</hi> of it. For there can be no more then is conveyed: Now we know, the people by their publike act of conſent and compact, may either bind themſelves to a full ſubjection to the Monarchs Will guided by his owne Reaſon; or by ſome conſtituted rule or law ſet him to governe by; which latter if they doe, then is his Authority radically limited: For they owing no more ſubjection; He can have no farther Power. 2. If ſoveraignty may be ſo limited, that Active Obedience is not <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> due to the commands which exceed thoſe limits, but may lawfully be denied to them (as the Doctour acknowledges it may, <hi>p.</hi> 16.) Then it may be limited in the Power it ſelfe: For in ſuch caſe the Power
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155066:17"/>
exceeds not the limitation; for if the exceeding Acts were <hi>poteſtative,</hi> we owe Active ſubjection to them, in as much as they are the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, to which <hi>in omnibus non prohibitis,</hi> Active ſubjection <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> is due. 3. If Power in the ſupreme be ſuch, that it cannot be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, then either becauſe it is <hi>Gods Ordinance;</hi> or elſe becauſe it is <hi>ſupreme:</hi> but its being <hi>Gods Ordinance</hi> hinders not; for we ſee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. All Powers as well ſupreme, as ſubordinate are Gods Ordinance, yet ſubordinate Powers may be limited, not only in the <hi>Rule of Acting,</hi> but in the <hi>kind of Acts;</hi> as none can denie. Neither its being <hi>ſupreme</hi> doth hinder its limitableneſſe; indeed, as before it hinders it from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable of confinement, in the <hi>kind of Acts:</hi> but <hi>in the meaſure or rule of working,</hi> it doth not hinder, in as much as a Soveraigne Power may as well attaine its end, by being confined to another Law from without, as by the Law of its own Reaſon, if not much better; alſo we no where finde Gods Word making any difference or giving pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to confine ſubordinate Powers; but forbidding it of Soveraignes. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> 4. That is to be granted, which denied makes all Soveraignes arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and of equall Power; but to affirme that Power is one, unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, and inveſting all the Acts of the Soveraignes Will doth ſo, for then is ſoveraignty arbitrary, not when it hath no <hi>morall</hi> bounds, for then none were or could be arbitrary; but when Power is ſo fully in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> one that every Act of his <hi>Arbitrium</hi> or Will is <hi>Poteſtative</hi> and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. 5. I have the judgement of all the Reformed Churches and Divines in <hi>Germany, France, Belgia, Scotland,</hi> on my part; who have both allowed and actually uſed forceable Reſiſtance againſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſive Inſtruments of their Soveraignes Will; yea our owne famous Princes <hi>Elizabeth, James,</hi> and our preſent <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> both by edicts, and Aſſiſtance have juſtified the ſame: which they would not have done, had they been perſwaded of ſuch an unlimited Ordinance of God inveſting all the Acts of the Will of him who is ſupreme. So that by all this it appears that the Doctors conceit of ſuch an unlimited Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, which he brings not a tittle of Gods word to prove, is a meere <hi>chimera</hi> and groundleſſe conceit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Object.</note>Now the onely difficulty, which I can thinke on, is this. Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in ſoveraignty, as before, is not onely <hi>Power</hi> to ſuch an end; but <hi>ſufficiencie</hi> of Power to the aſſecution of that end: now a limited Power ſeemeth not to be ſufficient for the end of Government, becauſe there are two Powers neceſſary to the end of Government, <hi>ſc.</hi> Power
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155066:17"/>
of <hi>making</hi> and authentique <hi>Interpreting</hi> of Laws, which are not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with a Limitation of Power.</p>
               <p>I anſwer: It is true of Limitation in reſpect of <hi>Acts;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sol.</note> and therefore I averre, that ſuch a Limitation cannot be where Power is <hi>ſupreme:</hi> but for Limitation to a <hi>Rule</hi> and defined way of Working, I cannot ſee how it with-ſtands the end of Government: So that ſuppoſing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>making</hi> and <hi>Interpreting</hi> Laws be neceſſary to the end of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet that they be Abſolutely reſident in him who is ſupreme, <hi>ſc.</hi> To <hi>make Lawes</hi> and <hi>Interprete</hi> Lawes authoritatively without being bound to follow any Light or Rule therin, but his owne Reaſon is not neceſſary to the end of Government: In theſe Acts a <hi>regulated</hi> Power is enough in the <hi>moſt ſimple State,</hi> ſc. a Power to <hi>make</hi> new Lawes, if any be needfull; and <hi>Interpreting</hi> the old, if ambiguous, according to the Rule of the former eſtabliſhed Laws; and by the adviſe of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſell and Judges of his ſupreme Courts of Juſtice. We ſee in matters ſpirituall, there is no Legiſlative Power reſident, to ordain or give authentique ſence in matters <hi>de fide,</hi> yet the Church ſtands well enough; one ſtanding Rule of Scripture being ſufficient with a <hi>miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Interpretation:</hi> So it is probable a State might, by a complete ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Rule of Law, and a Miniſteriall Power of Interpretation, were there no Legiſlative Power reſident in any Supreme Magiſtrate thereof.</p>
               <p>But the matter is farre more cleare in a <hi>mixed Government;</hi> ſo that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>2</label> were it neceſſary in a <hi>ſimple</hi> Government, that the Supreme ſhould be unlimited in his Power, yet in a <hi>Mixed</hi> (which is enough for us in this Kingdome) evidently it is not ſo: And to make this appeare, I will lay downe three grounds. 1. Such a Government may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed that the ſupreme Power may be placed in many perſons, either of the ſame, or divers condition, that is, in a mixed Subject: elſe all formes were unlawfull except ſimple Monarchie. 2. If this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Power be inequally placed in theſe Perſons or States of men; ſo that a reall ſublimity and Principality be given to <hi>one,</hi> then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination may be taken from that Principall: and ſo it is a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, or Ariſtocracy, or Democracy <hi>mixed</hi> in the <hi>Power it ſelfe;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it pleaſeth this Replier to deride it, with <hi>the top,</hi> or <hi>Crowne of the head:</hi> of which more hereafter. 3. Where the Supremacy of power is thus in many, although all taken together have an unlimited Power, as in ours, yet neither of them ſeverall by himſelfe hath, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155066:18"/>
can have; for it is a contradiction, that it be reſident in <hi>many,</hi> and yet unlimitedly in <hi>One.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to thoſe two ſhewes of Argument, which in the beginning I produced out of this Reply, I ſay, before Government be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it is true the people have no <hi>formall Politique Power</hi> of Life and Death; yet they have a <hi>ſeminall;</hi> that is, every one for himſelfe, his family and poſterity hath a power of reſigning up their naturall liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be governed by One, or many; after this or that forme as they ſhall judge fitteſt. God ordaining that Powers ſhould be to ſuch an end, hath thereby legitimated and ratified any Conſent or Contract which people may make of parting with their liberty and giving Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates a common Power over them to that end. And Gods not preſcribing any <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Meaſure</hi> of Power by his Ordinance of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, hath left it in the peoples liberty, to reſigne up themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſuch Rule and Termes, as they judge fitteſt, ſo it be ſuch as the end of his Ordinance may be attained thereby. Thus although by it ſelfe, and excluding Gods Ordinance they have no immediate Power to lay a command on others, nor Power of life and death, yet in vertue of Gods Ordinance their common conſent and contract is ſufficient to ſet up ſuch a Power which is endowed with a ſufficiency of Command for <hi>Government</hi> and the <hi>end of Government</hi> over thoſe which have, each man for himſelfe and his, ſet it up. So although <hi>ſecond Cauſes</hi> have no Power by themſelves to produce their effects, yet working in vertue of the <hi>firſt Cauſe</hi> they have Power to produce effects, ſometimes farre beyond their own Meaſure. Therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this Doctour either to bring ſome <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> expreſſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to ſet any <hi>bounds</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> of Power upon the <hi>Will</hi> of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; or elſe let him ſuffer Man-kind to uſe their <hi>Right</hi> in reſigning up that liberty which God and nature hath given them upon ſuch termes and conditions as they apprehend beſt for their own good: and the due end of Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Summe.</note>In the cloſe of this Queſtion, I will lay downe three Concluſions concerning the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and <hi>the Nature of Soveraigntie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>1</label> 1. <hi>God hath ordained that in Societies of Men there ſhould be a Politike Power, for a peaceable and godly life:</hi> This Ordinance hath put a <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Power</hi> in all the Societies of Men, ſc. a Liberty and Power by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Conſent to reſigne up themſelves and theirs to one Supreame; thereby conſtituting a <hi>common Politique Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:155066:18"/>2. <hi>God in his Ordinance for Government having not determined any kind <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> or forme of Power; hath left it to the libertie of Societies of men to chooſe to which kind they will reſigne up themſelves,</hi> either to a ſupreme regulated in the Acts of his Will by his <hi>owne Reaſon,</hi> as in abſolute Government; or to one regulated by a <hi>Common Reaſon</hi> or Law conſtituted by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conſent, as in Limited.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>God in his Ordinance for Government having not determined the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> of this Power, hath left it to the choice of Societies to inveſt with this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigntie, either one Perſon or many, and thoſe either of the ſame, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſorts and rankes of men;</hi> Whence ariſe ſimple or mixed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and this is the <hi>Architectonicall Power</hi> left in ſocieties before they are engaged in a Government, which the Doctour doth ſo cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly deride: Here is the ſumme of what I do averre concerning <hi>Gods Ordinance in Soveraigntie,</hi> which I challenge the Doctour or any elſe to gain-ſay.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of the Doctors falſe ſuppoſals reſpect the <hi>Nature</hi> and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Quality of Limitation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of nature and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</note> where alſo I obſerve that he proceeds on two falſe and fallacious Principles, <hi>ſc.</hi> 1. He every where confounds <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> and <hi>Civill</hi> or <hi>Legall</hi> Limitation, ſo <hi>p.</hi> 18. 93. 39. 2. That Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is capable onely of a <hi>morall</hi> Limitation, <hi>p.</hi> 39, 42., So that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other be in any State ordained, <hi>He cannot beleeve but ſuch a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is unlawfull, and unreaſonable againſt the Order of Government. p.</hi> 39. If the nature of <hi>Limitation</hi> be well knowne, it will appeare that the Doctor hath done very inconſiderately, or rather very fraudulently (for he hath obſcured the Truth much by it) in confounding <hi>morall</hi> and <hi>Civill Limitation.</hi> We will therefore conſider the nature of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation</hi> ſomething more accurately then I have done in my former Treatiſe; for it will be a great light to the whole controverſie.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We muſt conſider a diſtinction of Power, which is either, <hi>A <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> ſimple Power of Willing</hi> or Doing, which is in every Morall Agent. 2. A <hi>Power of Authoritative</hi> and <hi>obligatorie Willing</hi> or Doing; ſo that an act of it, whether a <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>Command</hi> or <hi>Cenſure</hi> expreſſed, hath in it a binding power to ſubjection, this is that which we call <hi>Magistracy,</hi> of whoſe Limitation now we treat.</p>
               <p>Secondly, concerning <hi>Limitation;</hi> we muſt know that it induceth <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> an abſolute <hi>neceſſity</hi> of not producing any Act beyond thoſe Limits. For a Power having bounds beyond which it can exceed, if it pleaſe, though with difficulty, it is not properly <hi>limited,</hi> but <hi>hindred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:155066:19"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, This <hi>neceſſity</hi> of not exceeding thoſe bounds is ſuch as the <hi>bounds</hi> themſelves are; ſo that it is ever true, <hi>That a Power in what way it is limited cannot exceed thoſe limits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>4</label>
                  <note place="margin">Of Moral limits.</note>Fourthly, There are of this Power but two ſorts of Limits, <hi>ſc.</hi> 1. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> and 2. <hi>Civill</hi> or Politique. Of which two we muſt diſtinctly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. 1. <hi>Morall Limits</hi> is the Morall Will or <hi>Law of God;</hi> and a Power is ſaid to be limited by this, not when it cannot produce any Act at all: but when it cannot <hi>morally</hi> produce it, that is, <hi>without ſin.</hi> For the ſupervening of a morall bond, doth not take away the <hi>Power of doing,</hi> but of right or <hi>ſinleſſe doing: v. g.</hi> in <hi>Naturall Powers.</hi> Gods prohibition of eating Swines fleſh, did not take away from the Jew the naturall Power of eating it; but the power of ſinleſſe eating it. So in <hi>Civill power</hi> a prohibition of God comming upon it, doth not take away the Power of <hi>Civill</hi> and Authoritative <hi>Doing;</hi> but of lawfull, or ſinleſſe doing. And hence it followes, 1. That Morall Limitation is only of the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of Power; not of the <hi>power</hi> it ſelfe: for the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is not thereby taken away, but remaines equally extenſe and able to all its acts, as it was before; only now it cannot put forth it ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to certaine Acts without ſinne, which it could before: Thus an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> Monarch who hath a power of doing, as extenſe as his Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Will, promiſes to doe but this, or in this manner: now he is <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bound,</hi> by vertue of this promiſe; and cannot without ſinne doe otherwiſe: yet if he doe, his Commanding Power is the ſame, and its act binding to the Subject. And ſo it is proportionably in <hi>Legall</hi> Governments. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> hath by the Canons a power of judging Eccleſiaſticall cauſes committed to him: He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves and promiſes to doe nothing of moment herein, but by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his <hi>Clergie,</hi> now he is <hi>morally</hi> bound: and if afterward he doe a thing by himſelfe without their conſent, he ſins: yet no man will ſay his Epiſcopall power is leſſened; or the act he ſo doth, is canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally <hi>invalid,</hi> and not obligatorie. 2. Yea it followes alſo that it is not properly a Limitation of the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of power neither: for by a morall bond, the Power is not ſo bound up, but that it can <hi>exerciſe</hi> it ſelfe, and that validly too, though not without ſinne, as appeares before. 3. Alſo that it is no detraction from <hi>Abſoluteneſſe</hi> of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; nor is it ſufficient to make a diſtinction of it into <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited.</hi> For, 1. It cauſes no reall Limitation of power, either in the nature, or exerciſe of it. 2. It is not <hi>diſtinctive,</hi> being to be found in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155066:19"/>
the moſt abſolute power under heaven,<note place="margin">Legall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits.</note> all being bounded by Gods Law, the Law of Equity, and many promiſes by themſelves made.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Civill</hi> or <hi>Legall Limits</hi> cauſe a <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Legall</hi> definement of Authority, ſo that, its exceeding acts are not <hi>Legall</hi> and binding, that is, are <hi>non Authoritative:</hi> for as a <hi>Morall</hi> bond induces a neceſſity of confinement in <hi>eſſe morali;</hi> ſo a <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Legall</hi> bond doth in <hi>eſſe lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li &amp; obligatorio.</hi> Hence follows, 1. It is theſe <hi>Legall</hi> and civill bounds which conſtitute a Government in a limited condition, not thoſe <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall;</hi> for this is <hi>diſtinctive</hi> and is never found in an abſolute Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for there the Soveraigne by promiſe or Oath binding himſelfe to a ſtated courſe doth put no Law civill upon his power, or the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it; for though he ſinne in exceeding afterwards, yet his acts are truely Legall and Authoritative. 2. This induceth a reall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of power, neither can it be only of <hi>exerciſe;</hi> for ſith it brings an illegality and unauthoritativeneſſe on acts exceeding, that is, makes them none <hi>in eſſe civili &amp; politico,</hi> it is a limitation of <hi>Power it ſelfe;</hi> for when a Power can produce no potentiall acts beyond ſuch limits, then it is limited in the very being. 3. <hi>Acts exceeding politique and legall Limitation,</hi> being not Legall nor authoritative in that State can give no authoritie to the Inſtruments, and therefore they may be reſiſted without reſiſtance or violation of Authoritie. Whereas it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in <hi>Acts exceeding morall Limitation;</hi> for being authoritative, they authorize the Inſtrument, and give him an unreſiſtance.</p>
               <p>In ſumme: Limitation morall and civill or legall doe differ in three main particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Morall,</hi> ſith it is no politique or Authoritative Act,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>1</label> makes no reall detraction either in power or exerciſe of it, and therefore agrees with the moſt abſolute Government: whereas <hi>Legall,</hi> being a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique and authoritative Act makes a reall diminution; and ſo is the <hi>ratio formalis,</hi> or <hi>diſtinctive conceit</hi> conſtituting Limited government; nor can be found in abſolute.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence, <hi>Exceeding Acts</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>morall</hi> limitation are <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> authoritative, proceed from Gods Ordinance, and challenge ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but they are otherwiſe which <hi>exceed</hi> a <hi>legall</hi> limitation.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Exceeding</hi> Acts in <hi>morall</hi> limitation being authoritative have the Sword or compelling power annexed to them, which may not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted: but in <hi>Legall,</hi> being not authoritative, they have not the ſword or compelling power annexed, and therefore may be reſiſted in their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155066:20"/>
Inſtruments: I will illuſtrate all this by a familiar inſtance. In our Government, a Iudge hath a Commiſſion to heare and determine Cauſes according to the Verdict of twelve men. Here is a Power li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited in the very being, that is Legally and Civilly. This Iudge uſeth indirect meanes to corrupt the Iurie to bring in an unjuſt Verdict; but judgeth as his Commiſſion binds him according to their Verdict: Here is a <hi>morall exceeding,</hi> yet the Act of judgement is Authoritative, becauſe according to his Commiſſion, and muſt not be reſiſted. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, He paſſeth ſentence in another cauſe expreſſely againſt the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of the Iury, in an arbitrary way. Here is a <hi>Legall exceeding,</hi> and the ſentence is <hi>non authoritative.</hi> He having no ſuch Power commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, the ſentence can have no binding power in it. Hereby it appeares how without any ground of Truth, the former ſuppoſals are.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Thirdly concerning the <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Meanes</hi> of Limitation the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſuppoſals are,<note place="margin">Cauſes &amp; meanes of Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 1. That <hi>Radicall Limitation,</hi> that is, of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it ſelfe requires <hi>an expreſſe and notorious act, it muſt be done in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and at once.</hi> p. 15. 24. 39. 2. <hi>That a Prince may ſo limit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as not to require to be actively ſubjected to, and yet be limited only in the exerciſe, not in the power it ſelfe,</hi> p. 16. 3. <hi>That no Limitation by after condeſcent, is of the Power it ſelfe,</hi> p. 28. this being a conſequent from the firſt. Now that the falſhood of theſe and the like grounds every where ſcattered in his bookes may appeare; Let us a little more diligently handle the <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Meanes of Limitation,</hi> which, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Cauſes of Moral Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</note> being twofold, Morall and Civill; We will begin with Morall. 1. Now the <hi>Formall cauſe</hi> of a meere <hi>Morall</hi> Limitation, is that which morally bounds or makes ſinfull any act of Power. We are therefore to enquire what it is which can doe that. And this is, 1. Principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Morall Law of God</hi> forbidding ſuch an exerciſe of Power. This is an <hi>univerſall, perpetuall</hi> and <hi>invincible</hi> Limitation of all power of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, either abſolute or legall, yea of all Active Power of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures. 2. There is another meane of Limitation morall, <hi>ſc.</hi> a <hi>Promiſe, Oath</hi> or <hi>poſitive constitution,</hi> whereby a Prince puts a bond upon himſelfe, making that now ſinfull to be done, which before was not ſo. This alſo induces a <hi>morall</hi> Limitation, as well in <hi>abſolute</hi> as <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> Governments; as if an Abſolute Monarch promiſe to follow ſuch a <hi>Rule,</hi> which hath a Power to uſe any which his <hi>reaſon</hi> ſhall dictate. Or if a <hi>Legall</hi> promiſe to abridge himſelfe in a courſe, in which the <hi>Law</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:155066:20"/>
hath left him indeterminate: in this reſpect, they come under a <hi>morall</hi> limitation. But concerning this <hi>poſitive meane</hi> we muſt note. 1. This promiſe, how ſolemne ſoever it be, muſt be a <hi>ſimple</hi> bond: It muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to no <hi>diminution</hi> of power, or <hi>diſcharge</hi> from duty of ſubjection; for then it is not meerely morall, it makes the exceeding act not only ſinfull, but non obliging: whereas it is the note of a <hi>meere morall bond,</hi> that it extends not to any leſſening of Authority, or diſcharge of duty: as if a Captaine take his enemy priſoner; he to ſave his life ſweares him a full vaſſalage afterward, his Maſter promiſes to command him only ſuch ſervices, never abſolving him from his former bond of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſlavery: here is a <hi>morall bond;</hi> yet ſtill a full debt of ſubjection in caſe the Maſter ſhould breake his word, and put him on other em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. 2. If the matter be more throughly looked into, this <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive meane</hi> of limitation is either none at all; or elſe addes nothing to the former, of the <hi>morall law of God:</hi> For in ſuch <hi>promiſe</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> whereby a Governour limits himſelfe there is an <hi>expreſſe</hi> or <hi>tacite</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if it conduce to the end of Government, the glory of God, and publick good: For if ſuch Oath or bond hinder the end of Government, it is <hi>eo nomine,</hi> unlawfull and invalid; but if conduce to it, then it was no more, then was virtually required of him before by the morall Law; this <hi>promiſe</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> being but a more ſolemne profeſſion and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to doe that which before implicitely he was bound morally unto. Thus we ſee all that Doctor ſpeakes of <hi>Morall</hi> and <hi>irrevocable limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> by promiſe and oath comes to nothing in the iſſue: ſo that this being granted that the Monarchs power in this State were only Moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly limited in the Doctors ſenſe; We are as much under and owe as much ſubjection as the captive ſlave to his Maſter; and all our Laws and Statutes being but morall limitations of this ſecond ſort, are not ſo much as <hi>morall limitations</hi> any farther then the Prince ſees them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the <hi>end</hi> of Government, if any ſeem to ſtand in his way, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him therein, he is no longer bound to it; but may account it an ill made <hi>promiſe</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> which is better broke then kept. 2.<note place="margin">Cauſes of Legall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</note> Of the <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Meanes</hi> of <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>legall limitation,</hi> whereby not only the <hi>exerciſe,</hi> but the <hi>power</hi> it ſelfe is confined. 1. The <hi>formall cauſe</hi> hereof is the limitation of the <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>ſubjection</hi> in the people: The <hi>duty</hi> of ſubjection is the originall of the <hi>power</hi> of Authority. People by becomming debtors of ſubjection doe ſet up Authority; and by ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and terminating the duty of ſubjection doe put bounds and termes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155066:21"/>
to the power of commanding. 2. Let us ſee then by what meanes the duty of ſubjection may be terminated. I conceive it may be done two wayes. 1. At firſt, when a people reſigning up themſelves to a ſtate of ſubjection doe it not abſolutely, but impoſe only a limited bond on themſelves; for if they impoſe no more <hi>duty:</hi> the Governour can aſſume no more <hi>power.</hi> Now this may be done, not only by <hi>poſitive,</hi> expreſſe and notorious act, as the Doctor ſpeakes; but alſo by a <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative;</hi> a meere not impoſing of an abſolute bond of duty on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves is enough: ſo that if it cannot be proved either by <hi>records</hi> of the firſt inſtitution, or <hi>preſent obligation</hi> that a people have put themſelves into a ſtate of <hi>abſolute</hi> ſubjection, then it is to be held but <hi>limited:</hi> For whatſoever is ours by the <hi>law of nature,</hi> cannot be taken from us but by ſome <hi>poſitive act</hi> done by our ſelves or Anceſtors: Thus in private men; Liberty which is mine by nature, none can take from me, unleſſe he can bring a title or right whereby it became his, and I his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Nor am I any farther his ſervant, then he can bring proofe of his right. The ſame is true of a ſociety of men. In this caſe it belongs to the <hi>challenger,</hi> and not to the <hi>defendent</hi> to bring his <hi>poſitive notorious act</hi> for proofe of his title, and meaſure of his title: So that the Doctors demand is unreaſonable, who ſtanding for a full right in our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, puts on the peoples part to bring evidence that they have not. Rather it is juſt, that he ſhould bring ſome poſitive and notorious act wherein it appeares that this people have fully reſigned up their liberty to an abſolute Government; or make it appeare that it is Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance that where ever a people doe conſtitute a ſoveraigne power, they muſt make an abſolute reſignation of their liberty. 2. By after-condeſcent, for this may be a <hi>meane</hi> of <hi>civill limitation,</hi> unleſſe any will imagine that a people once putting themſelves into abſolute ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, are irrevocably ſo. And thus a Monarch becomes <hi>limited,</hi> when the <hi>promiſe</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> he limits himſelfe by, is not <hi>ſimple,</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts either expreſſely or equivalently to a <hi>relaxation of the bond of ſubjection:</hi> whether it proceed from meere grace, or conſcience of equity, or by Petition, or importunity of the people, it matters not what was the ground of it, if it carry with it a <hi>relaxation of the dutie of ſubjection,</hi> it is a <hi>meane</hi> of <hi>civill limitation,</hi> in the very <hi>root</hi> of <hi>power;</hi> for <hi>power</hi> can be no larger in the Prince, then <hi>duty</hi> of ſubjection is in the people; for theſe two have a neceſſary dependence, and <hi>relation of equality</hi> either to other. Thus if a Monarch, taking advantage of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155066:21"/>
force of armes, impoſe a new Oath of <hi>full ſubjection</hi> on his people, who before were but <hi>legally</hi> bound; and prevaile ſo farre, that the <hi>whole</hi> or <hi>major part</hi> of his people doe take it for themſelves and theirs, here is a <hi>chang</hi> of Government from <hi>Legall</hi> into <hi>Abſolute,</hi> an enlargement of power: ſo on the contrary. And for this matter we need looke no farther, then the <hi>Nationall Oath,</hi> or <hi>Eſtabliſhed Lawes;</hi> for if they bind the people to an <hi>abſolute ſubjection;</hi> ſuch is the power; and though it have morall, yet it hath no legall limitation: And ſo on the contrary if they bind only to a <hi>ſubjection according to the Law;</hi> the Government is limited in the very <hi>power</hi> of it. Hence it appeares to be falſe which the Doctor hath, <hi>p.</hi> 16. that a Monarch may ſo tye him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as <hi>to require not to be ſubjected to but according to ſuch Lawes,</hi> and yet not be civilly limited, in his very power; for if he ſo far <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> not to be ſubjected to, that he untye the bond of ſubjection beyond thoſe Lawes; then is his Authority limited, and can proceed no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; neither are the inſtruments of his will exceeding thoſe lawes, authorized, but private perſons, and reſiſtible: And alſo falſe, which he ſayes, p. 28. <hi>That limitation by condeſcent cannot be radicall.</hi> Now if enquiry be made concerning the <hi>ſimplicity of antient formes</hi> of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into ſoveraignty, as when the people are ſaid to make one King; to endue him <hi>indefinitely</hi> with Kingly power; not confining his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by any expreſſe limitations. <hi>Anſ.</hi> I conceive in ſuch caſe to know how far a people are bound by ſuch an <hi>indefinite contract,</hi> theſe things are to be looked into. 1. If the <hi>intent</hi> of the people can be diſcovered in ſuch a conſtitution, for if it can, doubtleſſe the contract binds ſo far, and no farther. Thus <hi>Lyra</hi> concludes concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the people of Iſrael for a King, that it is to be underſtood of an Abſolute King, by that clauſe in the petition, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5. <hi>a King to judge us like all the Nations,</hi> for all thoſe Eaſterne Nations having Abſolute Monarchs, they deſiring to be governed like them; muſt be conceived to intend ſuch a government. 2. If there be no expreſſion of their <hi>intention:</hi> then a light concerning it muſt be borrowed for circumſtances; <hi>ſc.</hi> the kind of government whereunto they have been formerly accuſtomed; or that of the Nation from which they procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: And thus the <hi>Saxons</hi> giving Kingly ſtate to their Captaines in this Land, cannot in reaſon be interpreted to intend any other, then that whereunto they were <hi>accuſtomed,</hi> and which was the <hi>forme</hi> of the Nation whence they came. This <hi>Rule</hi> is ever to be kept as well in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155066:22"/>
as in private contracts of that ſimple indefinite forme, that <hi>they are to be construed, as far as may be, in fovour of the granter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> An Anſwer to the <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> concerning the Conſtitution of this Monarchy.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> A Fourth ſort of the Doctors <hi>ſuppoſals</hi> are concerning the <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of this Monarchy, which in words he granteth to be <hi>limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>mixed,</hi> but comming to explaine himſelfe, he makes ſuch a <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation</hi> of it and ſuch a <hi>mixture</hi> as is indeed none at all, being to be found in the moſt Abſolute and ſimple governments in the world: for he every where ſuppoſeth it limited only <hi>morally in the exerciſe,</hi> not in the <hi>power:</hi> And ſo mixed, that there is but one <hi>ſimple power; a mixture made of one ſimple principle,</hi> ſuch a one as never was heard of in the world before. And this he delivers on his bare word, never bringing any proofe of it, thinking it enough if he can except againſt that which I have ſet downe concerning theſe things in my Treatiſe. Among other Aſſertions which I have there about the ſtate of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: there are two which this Replyer doth oppoſe. One is p. 31. <hi>That the ſoveraignty of our Kings is radically and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally limited:</hi> which I have made good by five Arguments, and added a ſolution to the two chiefe which may be made againſt it. The other is, p. 39. <hi>That the Authority of this Land is of a compounded and mixed nature in the very root and conſtitution of it.</hi> This I have confirmed by three Reaſons; and have anſwered three Objections which may be made againſt it. Now I deſire the Reader impartially to weigh what I have there ſaid; and to compare it with this Doctors Reply; and then judge whether thoſe truths ſtand not firme againſt all that is brought to infringe them. But let us ſee what he oppoſeth. He proceedes not in any orderly courſe, to ſet downe his <hi>Antitheſes</hi> and prove them; and to give Anſwer to what I have brought on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; but firſt ſpends ſome time in conſidering what this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was in its <hi>Originall;</hi> as if it muſt needs remaine ſtill ſuch as it was at firſt; and could not receive any alterations, and graduall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment in proceſſe of time. And then he ſets on my Arguments, but how feebly we ſhall eaſily diſcover.</p>
               <p>Here the firſt thing I did tax in the Doctors booke, was that he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med things contradictory: for <hi>he tells us he is againſt Abſolute power
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155066:22"/>
in our Kings; and arbitrary Government:</hi> And yet he alſo affirmes, <hi>that our Kings hold by right of conqueſt, yea of three conqueſts.</hi> And that the <hi>Houſes of Parliament</hi> are more ſubject to our Kings, then the <hi>Senate of Rome</hi> was to their Emperours. Alſo that <hi>the finall judgement is in One.</hi> Now how theſe ſo openly contradictorie Aſſertions can ſtand together he doth not ſhew us. <hi>Only he challengeth my ingenuity, if either he propoſed this as a concluſion to be proved, that our Kings are abſolute,</hi> p. 21. Neither doe I affirme that he did: Only I ſay, he holds things contradictory; that he holds ſuch grounds which make all Kings abſolute, <hi>ſc.</hi> that no <hi>ſupreme</hi> is or can be more then <hi>morally</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited. Indeed he ſpeakes much of limitation morall; of limitation in the exerciſe of power; this makes a great noiſe of <hi>limitation,</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are but meere vailes to cover over Abſoluteneſſe, and make it the more paſſable, which he is aſhamed to propoſe to the world in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe termes. Suppoſe he did not <hi>mention thoſe conqueſts to win an arbitrary power to the King.</hi> Yet ſure in affirming more then once, that he hath ſuch a right, he doth as much as if he ſaid he may uſe an arbitrary power if he will; for if he hath a <hi>right of Conqueſt,</hi> he hath an <hi>Arbitrary right,</hi> by the Doctors own confeſſion, <hi>p.</hi> 22. and if he hath a <hi>right of Arbitrarineſſe,</hi> it is his lenity he doth not uſe it. In the Anſwer to the firſt Argument which I brought for the Abſoluteneſſe of our Kings (which was that <hi>They hold by conqueſt, and therefore are Abſolute.</hi>) I do not ſay, the Doctor drawes ſuch a <hi>concluſion:</hi> No; but he layes down the <hi>Antecedent;</hi> and then any body elſe may draw out the concluſion.</p>
               <p>I fetch not the root of ſucceſſion, ſo farre backe as the <hi>Saxons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Originall of this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</note> as this Replier traduces, <hi>to cut off advantages which may be made from the Normans entrance,</hi> p. 22. But becauſe himſelfe began there to make up a <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Conqueſts:</hi> This drew me on that diſcourſe of the <hi>Originall</hi> of this Monarchy; nor that the cauſe had any need of it; for it is his work to prove the Government abſolute, if he will have it ſo; alſo ſuppoſe it were as abſolute as the <hi>Norman Conqueſt,</hi> by him improved can make it; yet that hinders not, but that it may become really and radically limited afterward, by <hi>condeſcent,</hi> as appeares in the former chapter. Concerning the <hi>Saxon</hi> entrance, I ſaid it was not a <hi>conqueſt, ſc.</hi> properly and ſimply, but <hi>an expulſion.</hi> He anſwers, <hi>This is neither true, nor greatly materiall,</hi> p. 22. I ſay, it is both <hi>true</hi> and <hi>materiall:</hi> It is <hi>true;</hi> for all the <hi>Britaines</hi> which retained their name and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155066:23"/>
were they many or few, were expelled into <hi>Wales:</hi> All the reſt <hi>in gentem, leges, nomen, linquam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, vincentium conceſſerunt;</hi> as himſelfe cites for me out of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cambden.</hi> And it is very <hi>materiall;</hi> for if they which only remained here <hi>in gentem &amp; leges vincentium conceſſerunt;</hi> Then the Conquerers, as I ſaid, kept their <hi>old forme of Government;</hi> the <hi>Saxons</hi> came not into the condition of the conquered <hi>Brittaines;</hi> but they into the old liberty of the <hi>Saxons.</hi> Hereupon grew there a neceſſity of inquiry into the Government of the Nation, before they came hither; that ſo we might know what a one they eſtabliſhed here; and brought the remaining <hi>Brittaines</hi> into. And a record of more unqueſtionable authority then <hi>Tacitus</hi> I could not imagine; nor a more expreſſe teſtimony for a limited forme in the very <hi>potestas</hi> of it; of which ſort he affirmes the Governement of all the <hi>Germane</hi> Nations was. How ever the Doctor is pleaſed to call it a <hi>conjecture,</hi> a <hi>dreame</hi> and <hi>uncertainty;</hi> No, the expreſſe teſtimony of ſuch an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour is not ſo: Rather that <hi>probability</hi> of theſe <hi>Saxons</hi> not being then a people of <hi>Germany,</hi> but did afterward breake out of the <hi>Cimbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca cherſoneſus,</hi> is ſo; which himſelfe dares call no more then <hi>a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</hi> I ſay, 1. It is a greater probability, that they were a people of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> before they came in hither; for the <hi>Angli</hi> which accompanied them in that invaſion, were queſtionles <hi>Germanes,</hi> and reckoned by <hi>Tacitus</hi> among that people, doubtleſſe they were neighbours in habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which were joyned in that voyage and conqueſt. 2. Suppoſe the matter were not cleare of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> yet is it of the <hi>Angli</hi> which gave denomination to the Land and people, who no doubt retained their Laws and Government, ſayes <hi>Cambden;</hi> which was <hi>limited</hi> in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>royall power</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus.</hi> But this Doctor would make men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, as if I endeavoured to deduce the very <hi>Modell</hi> of our preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from that <hi>Saxon</hi> ingreſſe: Whereas all that I ayme at, is to make it appeare that <hi>in ſemine,</hi> in the <hi>rude beginnings</hi> it is ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; and ſhall affirme the limited power of the Engliſh Kings, and liberty of the ſubjects to have been from thence continued till now, unleſſe he can bring ſome better proofes of its interruption, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of an unlimited power, then as yet he hath. Alſo to ſhew that the Doctors Tenure by Conqueſt is vaine in the firſt of the <hi>Three,</hi> for the <hi>Saxons</hi> gave none ſuch to their Princes, but kept their Lawes, and came not under the Title of a conquered people. Next, the Doctor cenſures my delineation of the preſent platforme of our Government,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155066:23"/>
                  <hi>p.</hi> 44. (for it is nothing with him for advantage to skip over 9. or 10. Pages) that ſo he might make a ſhew as if I ſet down that <hi>modell</hi> as derived from the <hi>Saxons</hi> out of <hi>Germany;</hi> and ſo ſpends neere two pages in this unreaſonable way of traducing me; Whereas he cannot be ignorant, that in many places, yea at preſent is forced to confeſſe, <hi>p.</hi> 24. that I acknowledge our Government came up to this exactneſſe and full height by degrees and in continuance of time; but indeed he had nothing elſe to ſay againſt that <hi>Deſcription</hi> of this <hi>platforme</hi> or any one of thoſe 6. <hi>Suppoſals</hi> of which it conſiſts; and therefore when he had fained as if I had derived it from the beginning of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Government in this Land, he calls it a <hi>phanſie, againſt the credit of all Histories and Chronicles,</hi> p. 24. and ſo lets it goe. Let the Reader judge, whether I doe not there apparently ſet it down as a <hi>deſcription</hi> of our <hi>now exiſtent Frame</hi> of Government: And whether any thing therein is not according to <hi>paſt hiſtorie,</hi> and <hi>preſent experience:</hi> Yea I chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the Doctor to except againſt the leaſt part of it, as not ſo: if he cannot, he doth wrong ſo to miſcall and deride it. After this Excurſion, he returnes back to the 36. page of my Book, and the proper buſineſſe of that Chapt. which was his <hi>three Titles by Conqueſt.</hi> I looked that after his <hi>firſt,</hi> he ſhould have made good his <hi>ſecond Conqueſt,</hi> ſc. the <hi>Daniſh,</hi> and made good what he had ſaid, that our Kings hold by that too, as one of the three. But not a word of that for ſhame: He paſſes p. 26. to the <hi>Norman</hi> entrance: And to prove that <hi>William</hi> held this Land by conqueſt, he cites out of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cambden</hi> that <hi>in victorie quaſi Tropheum, he diſpoſed of the Lands of the Conquered, changed their Tenure, abrogated what Engliſh Lawes and customes he pleaſed,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed when he had gotten full poſſeſſion, he did what he pleaſed; but <hi>ſactum non probat jus.</hi> I have proved, and the Doctor hath not gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, 1. That his <hi>Title</hi> by which he claimed was <hi>a ſucceſſive and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Title.</hi> 2. That this <hi>Title</hi> got the favour of a great party, and was <hi>a maine Meane</hi> facilitating his acquirie. 3. That he was <hi>inaugurated by virtue of that Title.</hi> 4. After he had gotten the Kingdome, though he did many things arbitrarily, yet <hi>he ſetled himſelfe and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in the state of Legall Monarches,</hi> as the Doctor confeſſes, <hi>p.</hi> 27. What then is become of his <hi>Triple Tenure by Conqueſt;</hi> when heres not one can be made good; when it comes to a due ſcanning? That of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cambden,</hi> that the Kings of this Land have <hi>Poteſtatem ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, &amp; merum imperium,</hi> is no more then that of the <hi>Statute</hi> which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155066:24"/>
the Doctor ſpeakes of, <hi>p.</hi> 47. that it is an <hi>Empire governed by one ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme head,</hi> which we acknowledge; for that <hi>merum imperium</hi> muſt be underſtood in a moderate ſenſe; elſe it ſayes more then the Doctor himſelfe profeſſes to own: Though M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cambdens</hi> judgement in this caſe is not of the authority of a proofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Then he paſſes to my Arguments, <hi>p.</hi> 28. But, by the way, let me tell him,<note place="margin">My Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Mixture vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> I brought 5. Arguments to prove this Government <hi>limited,</hi> and 3. to prove it <hi>mixed:</hi> and it had been meet he ſhould have brought ſomewhat, beſide his bare word, to prove it limited only in the <hi>exerciſe,</hi> that is, <hi>Abſolute in the power;</hi> but he brings no proofe, becauſe he had none: Yet perhaps though he had not wherwithall to <hi>confirm</hi> his own, yet he hath to <hi>demoliſh</hi> my Aſſertions: Let us ſee therefore his <hi>ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of my Arguments. But before we come to weigh them, becauſe he tells us p. 28. <hi>it were an Argument fit for a skilfull Lawyer to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in, and ſlights</hi> my endeavour becauſe I bring not Hiſtory and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, but doe goe about <hi>to reaſon him into a beliefe of thoſe Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Let me premiſe ſomething concerning that courſe of proving them. 1. The work of bringing <hi>History</hi> and <hi>Antiquity</hi> doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him who affirmes ſuch a Title of Power in our Kings; Let him ſhew how and when it was conveyed to them: He which challenges a right to that which was once undoubtedly mine, muſt prove his right and he can have no more then he can bring evidence for. 2. On his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faut, if I undertake a needleſſe office to prove my <hi>Negative,</hi> there are but two wayes imaginable to doe it, one is by <hi>records of hiſtories</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the <hi>firſt conſtitution</hi> of a ſtate, and the <hi>Termes</hi> on which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> people reſigned up their liberty to a ſubjection. So in the Antient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> State, the <hi>Venetian,</hi> the late <hi>Belgik <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and others which have at once, viſibly and lately been compoſed, it is likely that way might be taken. The other is by <hi>demonſtrative collections</hi> drawn from the inſtitution of the preſent compoſure of a State. Thus alone is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to diſcerne and prove the <hi>conſtitution</hi> of a Government which ſprings not up at once, but by unſeen degrees and moments, whoſe fundamentall conſtitutive acts ſtand upon no record. This is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of moſt Governments in the world which have ſprung from ſmall, rude and unknown beginnings. And of this in particular. For 1. A limitation of Royall Power was brought hither by the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Angli</hi> our Anceſtours, hath been proved. This was, as thoſe times were, very <hi>rude</hi> and <hi>unpoliſhed,</hi> it is likely ſuch as <hi>Captaines</hi> in Armies
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155066:24"/>
have, who can doe nothing of moment without the adviſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the <hi>Counſell of warre.</hi> 2. This Limitation of Power and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie received ſome more <hi>formall</hi> and ſetled bounds afterwards by <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> and <hi>Lawes</hi> before the Conqueſt, as appeares by the <hi>Common Lawes,</hi> which are, as it were, the <hi>baſis</hi> and <hi>foundation</hi> of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Statute Lawes</hi> being but after <hi>ſuperstructives;</hi> Theſe <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawes</hi> did not grow up at once, but by degrees, and were <hi>unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Customes and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages</hi> gaining authority by unknowne preſcription, above all written Lawes; and were afterward committed to writing by men skilfull in the Lawes. 3. At length, and after the Conqueſt it was perfected to this <hi>Parliamentarie Forme;</hi> and even this being at firſt but <hi>rude,</hi> grew to this <hi>exactneſſe</hi> by length of Time, and infinite Contentions. This latter way only being left us; that I took, and the Doctour hath no cauſe to deſpiſe it. For when a thing of <hi>preſent State</hi> is made evident by Reaſon drawne for palpable experience of it's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent compoſure, it is madneſſe to denie it to be ſo, becauſe I cannot tell when it began to be ſo: Yea when the Queſtion is of <hi>preſent ſtate,</hi> it is a ſurer way to find out the Truth, then by records of its Originall conſtitution: For in time the Frame of a State may receive reall varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from what it was at firſt, as the <hi>Romane State,</hi> and moſt others have done; for the contracts of men are at pleaſure alterable; and an argument drawne from Monuments of firſt coalition, would then be fallacious.</p>
               <p>Well; be the way never ſo juſtifiable, which I have taken, yet the Doctor <hi>dares pronounce my Arguments inſufficient to cleare what I have undertaken.</hi> Tis eaſie to pronounce it; let us ſee how he makes good his ſentence. I proceeded diſtinctly firſt to lay down my Arguments proving <hi>Limitation,</hi> p. 31. Then thoſe which proove <hi>Mixture,</hi> p. 40. He mingles them together: And to my firſt, third, fourth and fift proving Limitation, Anſwers that <hi>They prove only limitation in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of power,</hi> p. 28. Why ſo? <hi>Neither the Denomination of Liege, nor any preſcription can make us believe, that the Limitations of power had any other beginning then voluntary condeſcent.</hi> As if a Government <hi>by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie condeſcent</hi> might not receive a <hi>radicall Limitation.</hi> But it lies on him to proove, it was by ſuch <hi>condeſcent;</hi> if he can bring no record for it, it muſt in juſtice be held <hi>originall,</hi> and <hi>ab initio.</hi> Thoſe two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations of <hi>Leige Soveraigne:</hi> And <hi>Liege people</hi> doe prove the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Soveraignty</hi> and <hi>Subiection</hi> Legall; but that is not ſo which hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:155066:25"/>
a morall Limitation; the denominations argue the <hi>bond 'twixt them to be Legall:</hi> And when Subjects have ſuch a Libertie by cuſtome and Law, that they owe no farther ſubjection, then (when, or how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they came by it) yet the very power of the Monarch is limited, as we heard in the former Chapter, unleſſe any will put a vaine power in the Prince, to which no Subjection is due; but of this enough there. Then he paſſeth to my <hi>Reaſons</hi> proving <hi>mixture,</hi> which are three, <hi>p.</hi> 40. of my Treatiſe. The firſt is, <hi>That it is confeſſedly mixed of a Monarchie, Ariſtocracie and Democracie, therefore radically, and in the very Power.</hi> He anſwers, <hi>It is not neceſſarie the mixture ſhould be in the Power: but it is ſufficient if there be a concurrence of Perſons whoſe conſent is required to the exerciſe of Power,</hi> p. 39. Thus he anſwers to the concluſion; but ſayes nothing to the Antecedent. 1. And indeed if it be mixed of theſe three, his anſwer is againſt <hi>common-ſenſe;</hi> that a <hi>mixture of Monarchie, Aristocracie</hi> and <hi>Democracie</hi> ſhould be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by annexion of perſons to the Monarch, having meere conſent: for theſe are <hi>names of Power of Government;</hi> for <hi>Ariſtocracie</hi> and <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracie</hi> are <hi>Powers</hi> not <hi>Perſons,</hi> as well as <hi>Monarchie:</hi> therefore a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of theſe three muſt be all of <hi>Powers.</hi> 2. And indeed this <hi>chimera</hi> of a <hi>mixture in the exerciſe of Power,</hi> is plaine <hi>non-ſenſe.</hi> For a mixture in the <hi>Acts</hi> or Exerciſe ſuppoſeth a mixture in the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Action,</hi> that is in the very Powers: A <hi>mixt Act</hi> proceeding from a <hi>ſimple Power</hi> is ſuch ſtuffe that I never heard before. Now if a <hi>mixture in Acts</hi> argues <hi>a mixture in Powers:</hi> Theſe <hi>Powers</hi> muſt be <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate</hi> and ſupreme: for <hi>ſubordinates</hi> make no <hi>mixture;</hi> alſo Powers concurrent to ſupreme Acts, ſuch as <hi>Legiſlation</hi> is confeſſed to be, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but ſupreme Powers. Neither can any man living cleare that paſſage which he ſpeaks of <hi>p.</hi> 45. from <hi>pure non-ſenſe,</hi> ſc. <hi>This coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is but to ſome Act or Exerciſe of the Supreme Power, not in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer it ſelfe:</hi> For <hi>Concurſe</hi> to an Act, im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lies a <hi>Power of Concurrence:</hi> and <hi>Concurſe to a ſupreme Act,</hi> argues a <hi>ſupreme Power;</hi> for an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Power cannot afford a coordinate concurrence to a ſupreme Act. So that his Over-ſeers were not miſtaken when they checked him for that paſſage, and ſaid, <hi>He granted a coordination of Subjects with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in the ſupreme Power.</hi> But here he brings a ponderous Reaſon, ſo often before urged. <hi>If the mixture be in the Supremacie of Power, how can the King be the Only ſupreme and Head. He cannot ſalve it with his</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pex poteſtatis, <hi>unleſſe the King muſt be the Crowne or Top of the Head
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155066:25"/>
onely; for they alſo muſt be our Head and our Soveraignes, if they be mixed in the Supremacie of Power,</hi> p. 29. Here I anſwer once for all to this ſo frequent an injection. 1. That the Titles of <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Supreme</hi> are fully ſatisfied by this, that he is the ſole Principle and fountaine from whence the execution of all Law and Juſtice flowes to his people by inferiour Officers and Courts, all whoſe Authoritie is derivatively from him as its head. 2. That theſe Titles in proper conſtruction import only <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tmoſt chiefty,</hi> nor doe they agree to any kind of right in the fundamentall and radicall Powers of a Kingdome; but to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and tranſcendent Intereſt: Another may have a right in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power, yet not be <hi>ſupreme,</hi> nor <hi>Head:</hi> becauſe not having a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie in that Power: So it is in the <hi>Colledges,</hi> the <hi>Fellowes</hi> have a fundamentall intereſt in the power of Government, yet that hinders not, but that the Title of <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Chiefe</hi> is given to him who is Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour; will the Doctour jeſt at it, and ſay they be <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premes too,</hi> and the <hi>Warden</hi> or <hi>Maſter</hi> is but the <hi>crowne</hi> or <hi>top of the head.</hi> Alſo in the <hi>naturall bodie,</hi> from whence the <hi>Metaphor</hi> of <hi>Head</hi> is borrowed, are three Fundamentall and radicall powers ſcituate in the three Principall parts: yet none will ſay, the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Liver</hi> are <hi>Heads</hi> too, becauſe they partake the <hi>ſupreme Powers</hi> of nature. Let not the Doctour therefore ſtraine a <hi>Metaphor</hi> ſo farre as to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe merry with it. Let him really anſwer my Arguments by which I prove a <hi>radicall Limitation</hi> and mixture. Let him anſwer; is not the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power the <hi>ſupreame?</hi> Have not the <hi>Houſes</hi> an <hi>Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive concurrence</hi> and Influx into that buſineſſe? If he avoyd a punctuall anſwer hereto by carping at words, he will prove himſelfe a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Argumentatour while he ſeekes to make others ſeeme ſo.</p>
               <p>My ſecond Argument for <hi>radicall mixture,</hi> is from the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power being in all three. He anſwers, <hi>That Phraſe is ſatisfied and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by that concurrence and conſent in the exerciſe of ſupreame Power.</hi> It ſeemes that invention of his muſt ſerve all turnes. Is a <hi>Legiſlative Power</hi> ſatisfied by a bare <hi>powerleſſe conſent?</hi> I demand: is that <hi>Conſent cauſall</hi> and <hi>Authoritative;</hi> or meerly <hi>Conſiliarie</hi> and <hi>unauthoritative?</hi> And whereas I prove that they have an <hi>enacting Authority</hi> by that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and ſet clauſe in the beginning of Acts; <hi>Be it enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie, and the Authoritie of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament.</hi> He tels us a <hi>Vote and Power of aſſenting is a great Authority,</hi> p. 29. I enquire not how <hi>great</hi> it is: I aske whether that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155066:26"/>
be all; whether that clauſe, which as expreſſely as words can, aſcribes an <hi>enacting Authority</hi> to them, be ſatisfied by ſuch a Power of Aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? He ſees it doth not, and therefore tels us of a former phraſe which ran thus: <hi>The King by the adviſe and aſſent of the Prelates, Earls and Barons, and at the inſtance and requeſt of the Commonaltie hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> &amp;c. Suppoſe anciently ſome <hi>ſtatutes</hi> runne under that <hi>forme:</hi> that <hi>adviſe</hi> and <hi>instance,</hi> muſt be underſtood of an <hi>Authoritative</hi> and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacting advice</hi> and <hi>inſtance;</hi> as the <hi>latter formes</hi> explaine it: for it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall that the <hi>latter</hi> expound the <hi>former;</hi> and not the contrary, as the Doctor would perverſly have it, eſpecially conſidering the Doctors Expoſition cannot ſtand with the <hi>latter;</hi> but mine agrees very well with the <hi>former.</hi> But how bold is this man, when during ſo many <hi>yeares</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> both <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>States</hi> by this received <hi>Forme,</hi> have acknowledged and eſtabliſhed a <hi>concurrent enacting Authoritie</hi> in all three, yet he dares argue and oppoſe ſo expreſſe and confeſſed a truth? But in this anſwer, he diſcovers a great deale of ſuperficialnes, in granting the Houſes a <hi>Power of conſenting</hi> to the eſtabliſhment of laws; and yet denie them a <hi>Legiſlative, enacting Power:</hi> for ſuch a <hi>Power of conſenting</hi> (if it be neceſſary) is indeed a <hi>Power of enacting;</hi> for though in <hi>tranſeunt Acts</hi> one may ſtand by and conſent to the doing, and yet not be <hi>Efficient;</hi> yet in <hi>immanent Acts</hi> which are done, <hi>per immediatam volitionem,</hi> by a meere expreſſion of the Will, A <hi>concurrence in conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and a <hi>concurrence in doing</hi> is one and the ſame thing: Now <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlation</hi> is an <hi>imminent Act,</hi> conſiſting in a meer <hi>expreſſion of an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative Will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My third Argument for <hi>Mixture,</hi> was from it's <hi>end,</hi> which was <hi>Reſtraint from exceſſe.</hi> 1. He <hi>grants</hi> ſuch a <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> but <hi>morall and legall, not forceable,</hi> p. 30. I anſwer, He deceitfully confounds <hi>morall</hi> and <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> as I ſhewed before. 2. The <hi>End</hi> of Mixture in a State, is that there may be a power of reſtreyning <hi>more then ſufficient</hi> (as his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie expreſſes it) but the Doctors meere <hi>morall</hi> power, is very <hi>inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient;</hi> It limits not the <hi>Power</hi> at all; nor the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> properly, no more then an <hi>Oath,</hi> or <hi>Promiſe</hi> without it, would doe: that is, makes it ſinne to exceed. But of this before. But here, which is very rare, He doth not onely denie, but give a reaſon of it. <hi>If the fundamentall Conſtitution had intended them ſuch a Power, it would not have left a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Monarch to call, or diſſolve them, which would make this power of theirs altogether ineffectuall,</hi> p. 30. This Reaſon ſeemes to have ſome
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155066:26"/>
weight in it, I will therefore, the more ſeriouſly conſider it. 1. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſtrength it hath had in it; now it hath none, becauſe that power of diſſolving is now by Law ſuſpended, for this Parliament; and after it, a neceſſity by Law impoſed of reducing that Power of Calling Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, into Act, every Three yeares. 2. Neither was it true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Acts, that ſuch a Power was left in the Monarch at pleaſure to uſe or not; for it was by ancient Law determined how often they ſhould be convocated. 3. But being granted that this Power is ſimply and fully in the Monarch, yet I denie, that hence it followes, that it would <hi>make that Power of the Houſes altogether ineffectuall;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that <hi>de facto,</hi> though it hath been in the Monarch ſo long, yet it never hath made it voyd; but they have exerciſed a limiting Power, as Hiſtories relate, enough yea and ſometimes too much, over the Monarch, notwithſtanding his Power of calling and diſſolving them. Thus in the <hi>Colledges,</hi> the <hi>Fellowes</hi> have an effectuall, and more then morall limiting Power, though the <hi>Governour</hi> hath the Power of <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and <hi>diſſolving</hi> their meetings. And anciently the <hi>prime Patriarch</hi> had the power of <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>diſſolving generall Councels,</hi> yet they had a <hi>Power of limiting,</hi> yea of <hi>Cenſuring</hi> him for exorbitances for all that. The Reaſon is, becauſe many things fall out oft in a Government, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing ſuch neceſſities on the Monarch, that he for their ſupply will chooſe to reduce ſuch power into act of Calling, and ſuſpend ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of diſſolving, although he know thoſe States will uſe their Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Power in reducing ſuch exorbitances, and puniſhing thoſe deareſt inſtruments which have been uſed in them. This the <hi>Conſtitutors</hi> of this Frame preconſidering might put in the Monarch this Power, and yet intend to the other States a <hi>Legall and effectuall power</hi> of reſtraining his exorbitancies, by uſing <hi>Force,</hi> not againſt him, but it's procurers and Inſtruments. Thus we ſee, there is no need of entring on that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, Whether this Power of calling and diſſolving the Houſes be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Monarch, as all his other are, not abſolutely, but with limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of neceſſary reducing it into act, on the laſt exigencies of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>After this he returns to my other Arguments for <hi>limitation;</hi> One of which, drawne from radicall Mixture, he fully omits; but now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhewed the invalidity of his exceptions againſt my arguments for it, I have given force to this argument for Limitation, drawne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. That which he ſets on laſt is my <hi>firſt</hi> for Limitation in the very
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155066:27"/>
Power: <hi>ſc.</hi> the Kings owne expreſſe confeſſion: <hi>That the Law is the meaſure of his power:</hi> That the <hi>Powers which he hath are veſted in him by Law,</hi> p. 31. of my Tract. And, as if this were not more then he could anſwer, the Doctor addes a <hi>third</hi> for us, in which he aſcribes to the Houſes a power <hi>more then ſufficient</hi> to reſtraine his Exceſſes, <hi>p.</hi> 30. Here are Authorities as punctuall and expreſſe as can be imagined. Yet the Doctor reſolving not to be <hi>reaſoned into a beliefe of theſe things,</hi> out faces all this evidence; and to that end frames three Anſwers ſuch as they are. 1. He ſayes, <hi>His Majeſtie had few of his learned Counſell about him.</hi> 2. <hi>His gracious expreſſions ought not to be drawne out to his diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</hi> 3. <hi>All that can be gathered from them doth not come up to theſe Concluſions, p.</hi> 31. In the two firſt he openly enough taxeth his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of unadviſed expreſſions, excuſing it from abſence of his learned Counſellours (you may ſoone imagine whom he meanes) Thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraging the Kings judgement and all then about him; and tels us we muſt not be unjuſt <hi>to ſet thoſe ſayings on the racke;</hi> that is, we muſt not take them in their plaine meaning; but on this mans wreſted and ſenceleſſe interpretation: What doe not theſe men dare doe and ſay? Before we heard him <hi>correcting</hi> the expreſſions of all Moderne Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, teaching us to reforme them by the old. Here the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Counſell</hi> ſetting out in ſuch a time <hi>Declarations</hi> to all his Subjects to informe them about the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>extent</hi> of his <hi>Royall Power:</hi> He compares thoſe ſerious expreſſes to <hi>Trajans</hi> ſudden and exceſſive ſpeech: He will correct <hi>Kings, Counſels, Parliaments</hi> and all, but he will have his way: To him they muſt come to learne how to ſpeake, and what powers they have. But let us heare his Doctorall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of his Majeſties expreſſes. Hee ſayes, <hi>The Law is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Power:</hi> Wee muſt underſtand <hi>his meaning to be that his power is bounded by Law: but it doth not follow, that his power wherein it is not limited by Law is not abſolute and full,</hi> p. 31. Here is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found interpreting: If his Power be limited by Law? is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of it not limited by Law? If the Law be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it, ſure it is even with it; for the meaſure is equall in extent with the thing meaſured: Thus he <hi>papally</hi> interprets againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect meaning of the Text: But he doth not ſhow us how that can be underſtood, when he ſaith, <hi>His powers are veſted in him by Law,</hi> if the Law be a limitation only of <hi>exerciſe:</hi> Nor how their Reſtraining po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is <hi>more then ſufficient,</hi> if it be only <hi>morall;</hi> which, how unſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155066:27"/>
a reſtraint for exorbitance it is, every ones experience can enough teſtifie. I admire a man who pretends to conſcience and judgement ſhould take ſuch liberty of interpreting. Certaine if thoſe Reaſons and Teſtimonies doe not clearly proove a <hi>radically limited and mixed Conſtitution</hi> of this Monarchy I ſhall deſpair of ever proving any thing by way of Argument any more.</p>
               <p>I had an intent to have ſubnexed other <hi>Arguments</hi> to make good <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> thoſe Aſſertions: but I ſee it is to no purpoſe,<note place="margin">7 Queries concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> for he is reſolved not to be <hi>reaſoned into them: He can denie all as failing either in the Antecedent or Conſequent,</hi> p. 32. The Power of this Kingdome he muſt have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited: He will give no <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it; nor heare no <hi>Reaſon</hi> againſt it. Yet, ſith he profeſſeth himſelfe a <hi>Reſolver</hi> of Conſcience, Let me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſo bold as to propoſe certaine <hi>Caſes</hi> to him. 1. Why in the late Oath propoſed to be taken by all his Majeſties Subjects the Power of <hi>enacting Statutes</hi> is ſworne to be joyntly in the <hi>Kings Maieſtie, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons in Parliament.</hi> Certes the Doctor writ this <hi>Reply</hi> before that <hi>Oath</hi> was printed in <hi>Oxford,</hi> or elſe he did not conſider of it. He cannot ſay, I hope there were but few of his counſell about him when that was framed: if the Doctor hath taken it, He hath forſworne this paſſage of his <hi>Reply;</hi> and ſworne them a joynt enacting power. 2. Why we are enjoyned to ſweare that <hi>we doe beleeve that the Subiects of</hi> England <hi>are not obliged by any Act made either by the Kings Maieſtie ſolely, or the Houſes ſolely,</hi> &amp;c. Sure the Doctor hath abjured his other <hi>Aſſertion</hi> of the <hi>unlimited Power</hi> of the King, if he hath taken this Oath; for if Power be ſolely his, then an Act made by him ſolely is obliging: If they be not <hi>obligatorie,</hi> they are not <hi>Authoritative;</hi> and ſo the mixture and limitation is in the Authority it ſelf. Here is no place left for his diſtinction of <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſion ſubiection.</hi> For, 1. Will any thinke that the intent is to ſweare men to be bound not to doe, but to ſuffer? 2. The <hi>Beliefe</hi> of a <hi>non-Obligation</hi> proceeds indifferently and as fully concerning the <hi>ſole Acts</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> us the <hi>Houſes</hi> but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the Doctour will not ſay we are obliged to <hi>paſſive ſubiection</hi> to the ſole Acts of the Houſes. 3. I would know if the <hi>States</hi> doe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit onely <hi>morally,</hi> what they doe, which is not done without them? A <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Oath</hi> do limit morally without them. He will ſay they may admoniſh him; and denie their conſent, and ſo iudge his Acts <hi>invalid:</hi> He meanes ſtill <hi>morally invalid;</hi> and ſo would they be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. 4. Suppoſe the <hi>Monarch</hi> minded to eſtabliſh a Law,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:155066:28"/>
which he judges needfull; and the States being averſe, he <hi>enacts</hi> it without them; Is it not a <hi>Law?</hi> It hath all the <hi>Legiſlative authoritie</hi> in it. He will ſay it is not duly made. 1. I grant it: but yet it is a <hi>Law,</hi> for it hath all the Power of a Law. 2. But is it not duly made? Why, the <hi>power of last deciſion</hi> is in the <hi>King alone:</hi> Suppoſe he define that the <hi>Intent</hi> of his Predeceſſours in granting this <hi>conſenting power</hi> to the <hi>Houſes</hi> had no intent to hinder, but further themſelves in eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good lawes; and therefore now they not concurring by aſſent to this needfull <hi>Act,</hi> He ought not to be hindred, but may lawfully doe it without them. He is the <hi>laſt Judge</hi> in this <hi>caſe;</hi> and it muſt be held ever <hi>lawfully enacted.</hi> So that in the reſult here is left to theſe <hi>States</hi> by the Doctors grounds neither <hi>Civill</hi> nor <hi>Morall Limitation,</hi> but at <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> 5. If Limitation in our Government exempt Subjects from a neceſſity of <hi>active</hi> Subjection; but not from <hi>paſſive;</hi> How is it that our Lawes doe not only determine what the Monarch ſhall <hi>command,</hi> but alſo what he ſhall <hi>inflict:</hi> what ſhall be accounted Rebellion, what Felonie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what not; alſo what he ſhall inflict for this crime, and that crime, and what not? Sith the Lawes limiting what he ſhall <hi>command,</hi> doe limit our neceſſity of <hi>active Subiection;</hi> it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the Lawes limiting what he ſhall <hi>inflict,</hi> doe limit our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>paſſive Subiection.</hi> Here's no evaſion by ſaying the Laws do limit him morally what he ſhall inflict, and if he inflict beyond Law, he ſinnes in it; but we muſt ſuffer: for the Doctor acknowledges, that the Lawes defining what he ſhall <hi>command</hi> doe ſo limit our active ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that we have a <hi>ſimple exemption</hi> from any neceſſity of <hi>Doing;</hi> and therefore alſo the Laws defining what he ſhall inflict, doe ſo limit our paſſive ſubjection, that we have a <hi>ſimple exemption</hi> from any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>ſuffering,</hi> beyond thoſe Limitations; for alſo, if they did not free us from paſſive ſubjection, it were unlawfull not only to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> but alſo to <hi>avoid</hi> ſuffering even by flight. 6. When the liberties of <hi>magna Charta,</hi> and other grants have been gotten and preſerved, and recovered at the rate of ſo much trouble, ſute, expence and bloud, whither by all that adoe was intended only a morall liberty, define<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Monarch, and not alſo of the power it ſelfe; only that he might not lawfully exorbitate from eſtabliſhed Lawes, and not alſo that he might have no Authority or Power to exorbitate at all? Sure this was their aime, for the former he could not doe before. 7. The Law granting a <hi>writ</hi> of <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt him who refuſeth to obey the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:155066:28"/>
ſentence of the Judge, though he have an expreſſe Act of the Kings will to warrant him: doth it not ſuppoſe thoſe <hi>exceeding</hi> and <hi>extrajudiciall Acts</hi> of the <hi>Kings will</hi> to be unauthoritative, and unable to priviledge a man from Reſiſtance?</p>
               <p>If the Doctor by his faculty can reſolve theſe <hi>Caſes,</hi> He will doe much in way of ſatisfaction of my conſcience; but if he cannot they will prove ſo many convincing arguments that the <hi>Power</hi> of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in this Frame is not <hi>unlimited.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now having made good my <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> I expected another worke; <hi>ſc.</hi> an <hi>Examination</hi> of his <hi>Reaſons</hi> for <hi>unlimitedneſſe,</hi> and <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of Monarchicall Power, but he is not guilty of my fault, he doth not goe ſo much as to reaſon us into a beliefe of it. He doth in vaine expreſſe a deſire hee hath that ſome skilfull <hi>Lawyers</hi> or <hi>Divines</hi> would helpe him at this dead lift; yet he is like to goe alone in this wild untroden path of defending an unreſiſtibleneſſe on ſuch ſuppoſals: ſhall we think any <hi>Divine</hi> will ſecond him, in juſtifying his unwritten fancie about <hi>Gods Ordinance neceſſarily inveſting all the acts of his will, who is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme?</hi> Or any ſound <hi>Lawyer</hi> will overthrow the grounds of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that the Royall Right, Authority and Government of this Realme is both founded on, and meaſured by the Laws thereof. Yea it is very remarkeable, that <hi>his Majeſtie</hi> in all the <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes</hi> which I have ſeen, doth not once touch upon this way, <hi>ſc.</hi> a chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of ſuch a latitude of Authority as can preſerve deſtructive inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from force; but condemnes the now Reſiſtance, by ſolemne <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations</hi> of innocency, and intention of governing by the <hi>known Laws.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> An Anſwer to his <hi>5. Sect.</hi> of Reſistance in Relation to ſeverall kinds of Monarchy.</head>
               <p>THE reſidue of his Book is ſpent about the Queſtion of Reſiſtance; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> I might well ſpare the labour of any farther Anſwer; for now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo apparently made good theſe two Aſſertions. 1. <hi>That ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may be limited in the very power.</hi> 2. <hi>That de facto, it is ſo in this Government,</hi> every one may diſcerne the neceſſary truth of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, 1. That in this Government, the <hi>exceeding Acts</hi> of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will, being out of the compaſſe of his Authority, can not authorize their Inſtruments. 2. That hereon <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> of them is no other then of private men, not of <hi>Authority,</hi> or <hi>Gods Ordinance.</hi> But becauſe the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:155066:29"/>
Doctors chiefe confidence is in this part of his diſcourſe, and he is large in it, I will therefore goe on in my work, and will briefly make appeare that his <hi>Reaſons</hi> are infirme, and his <hi>Authorities</hi> impertinent, and his <hi>Anſwers</hi> very inſufficient: for having been ſo large in making good my <hi>ſuppoſals,</hi> and overthrowing his, I may the more contract my ſelfe in this remaining buſineſſe. In this Section he propoſeth two things. 1. To conſider how I <hi>ſtate the point of Reſiſtance</hi> in the kinds of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments. 2. To prove that <hi>Limitation and Mixture in government doe not imply a forceable conſtraining Power in ſubjects,</hi> p. 39. I will follow him in both.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">My ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Queſtion vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>He begins with a charitable cenſure of my ſtating the Queſtion, and ſayes <hi>he finds it to be in a way that lies very open to Rebellion,</hi> p. 33. Let the Reader judge: I am ſure, his <hi>Reſolves</hi> and <hi>Determinations</hi> are not in a way to deſtroy all <hi>liberty,</hi> and make all Governments <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> but directly doe it. Then for my maintaining the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the Monarch in <hi>all Formes</hi> to be above the reach of Force, he approves it; yet ſayes <hi>I allow ſubjects to raiſe Armies, to give battle to thoſe that are about him as his guard.</hi> He wrongs me, I ſay not <hi>his guard</hi> but <hi>ſubverſive ſeducers and inſtruments:</hi> Thoſe which he called <hi>cut-throates</hi> in his firſt booke; now he repents he gave that hard name to his clients, whom he pleades ſo hard to ſave harmeleſſe, and makes them amends with the ſtile of a <hi>Guard.</hi> A guard which bring him into grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter danger then all his enemies; who bring him into battell to ſave themſelves, where <hi>Ordnance</hi> and <hi>Musket</hi> can put no difference: No; <hi>They uſe him as their guard.</hi> If harme befall him, which God avert, the guilt and puniſhment will fall on them who are ſo prodigall of hazarding his ſacred Perſon, not on thoſe who could deſire nothing more then his ſecurity, by abſence from a multitude, who by underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſubverſion of Religion and Lawes (for that is the Doctors ſuppoſition) bring themſelves in danger of condigne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Then he proceeds to Reſiſtance in an <hi>Abſolute State.</hi> Where I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, <hi>If ſuch a Monarch ſhould ſeeke the deſtruction of the whole Community, his inſtruments of ſuch inhumanity may be reſiſted.</hi> He dares not deny it; but would know what I doe meane by the <hi>whole community.</hi> I meane the <hi>whole ſimely,</hi> or the <hi>whole interpretatively;</hi> that is, the greater part; and therefore his exception of the <hi>Jewes</hi> in the Kingdome of <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> or the <hi>Templers</hi> in the Weſterne King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, is not to the purpoſe: but the inſtance which I bring of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155066:29"/>
                  <hi>Law-Countries,</hi> comes home: for they were the <hi>whole community;</hi> but the <hi>Replier</hi> corrupts it, when he ſaith <hi>the Spaniſh King intended the extirpation of the Proteſtants only,</hi> p. 34. For he intended not only theirs, but of all, Papiſts and elſe, which would not admit the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction of an Arbitrary Government, and the ſubverſion of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, as the hiſtories thereof make plaine. Here in this 34. page, the Doctor ſhewes a bad mind: Taking occaſion to excuſe the <hi>Rebels</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as if they might juſtifie themſelves on theſe grounds; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating a falſhood, as if the Parliament did intend their extirpation, hereby declaring how ill he likes any effectuall courſe for the rooting out of Popery out of the Kingdomes. Indeed, he ſayes, <hi>he pleads not for them,</hi> but yet he doth it. He finds out arguments for them; and ſhews them a way, both how to excuſe themſelves, and accuſe the Parliament; and to call a reſolution of cleanſing that Iland from Popery, an extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of their Nation. He ſayes, the <hi>example of David proves not this, being but a particular Man.</hi> I ſay, it proves it the more ſtrongly, as ſhall appeare. Then <hi>if a particular mans life be invaded without any plea of reaſon, I ſuppoſe it hard to deny him the liberty of poſitive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of agents;</hi> and prove it by the inſtance of the peoples reſcue of <hi>Jonathan;</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> of himſelfe; where the peoples <hi>Oath;</hi> and Davids <hi>Army,</hi> with his <hi>enquiry</hi> at <hi>Keilah</hi> doe prove a ſerious and reall purpoſe of Reſiſtance, let the Doctor ſay what he pleaſe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſo that theſe examples come home to juſtifie reſiſtance in ſuch caſe, even in an <hi>Abſolute Monarchy;</hi> for here are particular men, in an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Monarchy, aſſaulted without <hi>plea of reaſon;</hi> for that <hi>Jonathan,</hi> who had wrought ſuch a deliverance, ſhould die, for taſting in his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance a little honey, there was no <hi>colour of reaſon;</hi> the Kings raſh oath was none. And that <hi>David</hi> ſhould be put to death, whom <hi>Saul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe oft with his own mouth profeſſed innocent, and abſolved, was as much without <hi>plea of reaſon:</hi> ſo that here I need not flie to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſhift of an <hi>extraordinary caſe,</hi> as he tells me I muſt, <hi>p.</hi> 35. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no extraordinary caſe in theſe examples: Take them in their due extent, and they juſtifie no more then I have aſſerted; and ſo much they doe. In my 5. Aſſertion, p. 11. <hi>Of ſubmitting States, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Perſons to the will of an Abſolute Monarch carrying any plea of reaſon;</hi> He faults my Order, and tells me, it ſhould have been firſt. It ſeems this mans eye can ſpie ſmall faults; but why firſt, he doth not ſay. I think in ſtating of the queſtion of reſiſtance I may as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:155066:30"/>
well begin with the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> and ſhew firſt when it may be uſed, and then when it ought not; as on the contrary; but he will make a fault, where he finds none. But what ſayes he to the <hi>Aſſertion?</hi> He grants it; but diſlikes the limitation, <hi>ſo it carry plea or ſhew of reaſon:</hi> and ſayes <hi>here the way is open enough to rebellion,</hi> p. 36. No opener then himſelfe makes it, <hi>p.</hi> 10. This is uſuall with him, when he diſlikes a thing: He can ſpeak no leſſe words then <hi>Rebellion.</hi> But why ſayes he ſo? <hi>Every man will be ready to think there is no reaſon nor equity in the will of the Monarch when he is oppreſſed by him.</hi> He may well enough, if hee be oppreſſed: but yet there may be a <hi>plea</hi> and <hi>colour of equity</hi> even for an Act of Oppreſſion; and in an Abſolute Monarchy it will little availe a man though he think there is no reaſon for it: for he muſt not be his own judge; nor hath he any outward judge to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to; but the <hi>Reaſonable will</hi> of the Monarch himſelfe; if he ſubmit to its determination, there is no feare of Rebellion; if not, I have done with him, in ſuch a Government. Of <hi>Saules</hi> cenſure of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> I have ſpoken already and made it appeare it had no plea of <hi>reaſon,</hi> was not the act of a reaſonable will; and therefore I may hold their examples ordinary, without impeachment of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion.</p>
               <p>Then he proceeds to Reſiſtance in <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>mixed Rules,</hi> p. 36. Concerning which I ſaid, p. 17. <hi>If the exorbitances be of leſſe moment they ought to be borne,</hi> and p. 18. <hi>If mortall and deſtructive neither can be otherwiſe redreſſed, then prevention by Reſiſtance may be uſed.</hi> Here firſt <hi>he challengeth my ingenuity,</hi> for words ſpoken in my 49. page. He ſaid Sect. 1. of his firſt booke, <hi>We may and ought to deny obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſuch commands of the Prince as are unlawfull by the Law of God; yea by the eſtabliſhed lawes of the Land.</hi> I cenſured this ſpeech, that <hi>it is more then ſhould be ſaid,</hi> ſure, a hainous fault in me: I ſay more; <hi>he hath ſaid more then ſhould be ſaid,</hi> by all theſe three bookes, in which he ſayes that which diſſolves all frames of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into arbitrary, overthrowes all effectuall limitation of Power; and ſure that is more then ſhould be ſaid. And for that particular clauſe; Is it not more? He ſpeakes without reſtriction: Doth joyne things unlawfull by the law of God, and things unlawfull by the lawes of the Land: And puts the ſame <hi>may</hi> and <hi>ought</hi> to both; if the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation muſt be underſtood <hi>univerſally</hi> of <hi>one,</hi> how can it be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood otherwiſe of the <hi>other:</hi> It cannot be excuſed from the cenſure
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:155066:30"/>
of a confuſed and unwary ſpeech. He paſſeth, <hi>p.</hi> 37. to the Queſtion, <hi>Who ſhall be the ultime judge of ſubverſive exorbitancies.</hi> He would know who? I have told him my opinion hereof at large in that Tract: Here I would faine know his; but he would rather carp at mine, then give his own. When I ſay there can be no <hi>Authoritative judge</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it. <hi>He commends my ingenuity,</hi> p. 37. but I doe not only ſay it, but at large doe prove it, there <hi>p.</hi> 67. as well againſt him, as againſt thoſe others; why doth he not undertake that <hi>Queſtion</hi> againſt me, if he hath any mind to it. He much diſlikes when I ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>The fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament all Lawes muſt judge in every mans conſcience. This is,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>a ready way to anarchy and confuſion,</hi> p. 37. I referre not this caſe to the conſciences of men as to an <hi>Authoritative Judge,</hi> but <hi>a morall principle of diſcerning Right:</hi> And who can deny unto man ſuch a liberty to conceive of right according to the light he hath from the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of a State? Let the judicious reade what I have ſaid here-about, <hi>p.</hi> 67. of that Tract; and let him then tell how that Queſtion can be otherwiſe determined, unleſſe he overthrow. <hi>Monarchy,</hi> by giving a finall judgement to the <hi>States;</hi> or all <hi>Liberty,</hi> if he give it to the <hi>Monarch;</hi> and ſuppoſing the <hi>Ayme at ſubverſion</hi> be evident to mens conſciences, can we deny them a naturall power of judging accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that evidence; or liberty of aſſiſting the wronged? So when I ſay <hi>the wronged ſide muſt make it evident to every mans conſcience: alſo the appeale must be to the Community, as if there were no Government; and as every man is convinced in conſcience he is bound to give aſſiſtance, p.</hi> 29. of my Tract: He calls this <hi>good ſtuffe,</hi> p. 37. Why? becauſe I ſay, <hi>the people are at liberty as if there were no Government; and this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale is diſadvantagious to the Monarch; for they will be more ready to believe their repreſentative: This would in the conſequence be dangerous, the high way to confuſion,</hi> p. 38. Anſw. 1. I ſay, not <hi>ſimply,</hi> that people are at liberty, as if there were no Government; but <hi>in this particular Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion;</hi> bound ſtill, as before, in all beſides. 2. He takes me as if by <hi>Community</hi> I meant only the <hi>Commons;</hi> when I expreſſe it by <hi>genus humanum,</hi> eſpecially of that Kingdome. 3. He cenſures the <hi>Reaſon of Man-kind</hi> of partiality towards their <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> Not ſo; for in ſo great a Queſtion <hi>Wiſe men</hi> cannot be blinded: <hi>Honest men</hi> will goe according to their conſcience, and <hi>Reaſonoble men</hi> according to evidence, and will ſee it concernes them as well to avoid <hi>Anarchy</hi> by aiding a wronged <hi>Monarch;</hi> as <hi>Tyranny</hi> by aiding an oppreſſed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:155066:31"/>
                  <hi>State.</hi> But ſith this <hi>Replicant</hi> is ſo bitter an enveigher againſt an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale ad conſcientiom generis humani,</hi> in this laſt caſe ſo uncapeable of an Authoritative deciſion: 1. Let him conſider on what foundation God hath built Monarchy and all other powers, but on the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2. Let him weigh whether, when he hath ſaid all he can ſay, ſuch an appeale be avoidable. For, 1. If a controverſie ariſe between the <hi>King</hi> and a particular perſon or place; the <hi>King</hi> ſhall Judge it in his Courts by his Judges, and the ſentence ſhall be executed by the force and armes of his other ſubjects. 2. If it be between <hi>Him</hi> and the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of his whole Kingdome, and ſupreme Court of Judicature in which the Acts and Perſons of all other Courts and Judges are to be judged. The King cannot judge this in his other Courts and by his Judges; nor yet by himſelfe; for a King out of his Courts cannot judge in a Legall Government, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the acts of his ſupreme Court. But be it ſo: ſuppoſe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and I ſhould agree in this, that the King by himſelfe is the <hi>ultime</hi> Judge of Controverſies: Yet it is very like thoſe <hi>States</hi> with whom the Contention is, will not yeild him ſo, to judge againſt them, in his own cauſe. But ſuppoſe they doe not ſubmit to his determination: He will ſay, then they ſin, and rebell againſt him. Well, let it be granted; yet ſubmit they doe not: I demand in this caſe, what courſe the King hath to make effectuall his ſentence? It muſt be by force of armes, by the ſword: but of whom? Either the <hi>peoples</hi> whoſe <hi>repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> they are; or other mens: but what ſhall bind them to afford their Force to make good his ſentence? It muſt be their conſcience of his right: Thus when all is done and ſaid, To the <hi>conſciences of Men</hi> muſt his <hi>appeall</hi> be; and to them muſt he make evident his right, in this extreme contention. Yea this man in a controverſie of the like nature, is compelled to acknowledge as much: For the <hi>Pleaders</hi> put the caſe; If a King be diſtracted, I may adde, if his Title be dubious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Doctors anſwer is, <hi>if it be cleare that a King is ſo, &amp;c.</hi> p. 8. but who ſhall determine this <hi>If?</hi> muſt not ſelf-evidence in the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Men? This is all the judiciall power the Doctour can referre us to in theſe caſes. Laſtly, <hi>He would know what power there is in a Community to make reſiſtance;</hi> and anſwers himſelfe, <hi>A Parliamentary and Legall; not Military and Forcible,</hi> p. 38. Thus he ſpeakes of theſe as contradiſtinct, when they are ſubordinate, <hi>Forcible</hi> being ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to <hi>Legall</hi> to make it valid and effectuall, which elſe were meerely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:155066:31"/>
morall and ineffectuall; but this is one of his ſuppoſals whoſe vanity I have before diſcovered: And <hi>p.</hi> 51. of my Treatiſe, in a full diſpute have I proved the Parliaments power in reſiſting deſtructive inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which I doubt not, will appeare cleare, notwithſtanding any thing ſaid in this Reply. But that is very ſtrange which he affirmes, p. 39. <hi>That if they uſe a Legall reſtraining power, the Monarch can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alter the establiſhed frame.</hi> Sure, by <hi>cannot,</hi> he underſtands falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, as he uſeth to doe, a <hi>morall cannot,</hi> that is, not without ſin; which is a poor ſmall <hi>cannot</hi> now adays: if he mean indeed <hi>cannot,</hi> that is, <hi>is not able,</hi> it is againſt reaſon, by his grounds; for what is not he able to doe, whoſe loweſt, moſt deſperate inſtrument of pleaſure is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible? Let him remember where he ſaid, p. 19. <hi>A forcible conſent cannot be wanting to a Conquerour,</hi> and a Conquerours power is no more then unreſiſtible. Nay; I am ſenſeleſſe on the Doctors grounds, if he cannot <hi>lawfully;</hi> for ſuppoſe he be pleaſed to make it a Queſtion, whether he were not better governe by the <hi>Civill-Law,</hi> as more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducent to Gods glory, and the <hi>end</hi> of Government. He is by Law the laſt judge of this Queſtion, if he determine it beſt: then he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully doe it.</p>
               <p>Now we are come to the ſecond part of this Section: in which he <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> undertakes the proofe of this <hi>Aſſertion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt power of reſiſtance reſerved. anſwered.</note> that <hi>Limitations and Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in Monarchy doe not imply a forcible conſtraining power in ſubjects for the preventing of diſſolution, but only a Legall,</hi> p. 39. <hi>Anſw.</hi> He failes in the very propoſall of his Aſſertion in three points. 1. He propoſeth it of Limitation in generall; whereas I grant it of that which is <hi>only in exerciſe;</hi> affirming it only of that which is of the <hi>power</hi> it ſelfe. 2. He ſayes, <hi>Forcible conſtraining power in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> when he ſhould have ſpecified <hi>againſt ſubverſive inſtruments,</hi> for I grant it of the <hi>Monarch</hi> himſelfe. 3. He oppoſeth <hi>forcible</hi> to <hi>Legall,</hi> when it ſhould be oppoſed only to <hi>meere Morall,</hi> not to <hi>Legall,</hi> as before. Now let us weigh his Arguments. Firſt, <hi>Such a power muſt be in them by reſervation, and then it muſt be expreſſe in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Government and Covenant,</hi> or elſe by implication. I will anſwer diſtinctly concerning this <hi>Reſervation of power</hi> of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Reſiſtance. 1. There is a <hi>Reſervation of liberty,</hi> or power of not being ſubject neither actively nor paſſively to the exceeding Acts of the Monarchs will: This is by <hi>implication,</hi> for what they did not reſigne up, they did reſerve. 2. <hi>A power of Authoritative judging</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:155066:32"/>
and reſiſting the Monarch thus exceeding. This neither expreſſely nor implicitly is reſerved; not becauſe it is <hi>unlawfull,</hi> as the Doctor ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, but contradictory to the very inſtitution of a Monarchy, and ſo, under that intention, <hi>impoſſible.</hi> 3. <hi>A power of forcible reſiſtance</hi> of ſubverſive inſtruments. This by the Authority of the Law, is, not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,</hi> but expreſſely <hi>commited,</hi> not only to the <hi>Houſes</hi> of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but all inferiour Courts; for the Law, whoſe execution the King committeth unto them, commands them not only to reſiſt, but puniſh its violaters, much more its ſubverters, without exceptions of <hi>Perſons,</hi> or reſpect of their <hi>number,</hi> or <hi>ground</hi> and reaſon why they doe it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with or againſt the Kings private and abſolute will or Warrant: ſuppoſing ſuch men to be without warrant. And this power of jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all violators and ſubverters of Laws being committed to them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a power of imploying the force or Armes of the County, or whole Kingdome, if need be, to make good the ſentence of the Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: <hi>This power</hi> being a neceſſary attendant to the <hi>former.</hi> And they who have the <hi>power of judging</hi> by Commiſſion, have the <hi>power of force</hi> by implication. To his five Arguments therefore by which he proves this power not <hi>reſerved by implication;</hi> I briefly Anſwer. 1. <hi>Limitation cannot infer it, &amp;c.</hi> Anſwer, Limitation in exerciſe only doth not: but in the power it ſelfe doth infer it, as I have often ſhewed. 2. <hi>The inconveniencies of exorbitancie cannot infer it.</hi> Anſwer, They doe not infer it of themſelves, for they are the ſame in abſolute Rule: but ſuppoſing a people mind in their Frame effectually to prevent thoſe inconveniencies, that doth infer it. 3. <hi>The conſent and intention of the people, chooſing a Monarch cannot infer it, becauſe it is not the meaſure of the power it ſelfe.</hi> Anſwer, I have before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the contrary, and made the Doctors ſuppoſall appeare a groundleſſe falſhood concerning unlimited power by Gods ordinance. 4. <hi>The intention of the people in procuring Limitations of power cannot infer it.</hi> Anſwer, If the peoples intention in it, be a greater ſecurity from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion then in an abſolute Government they can have, or a meere mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall limitation can give them; then it doth inferre it. 5. <hi>If the Architects did intend ſuch a forceable power to theſe States, they would not have beſt it in his power to diſſolve them,</hi> p. 42. This hath had its full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction before. Theſe are poore infirme arguments, as the reader cannot but ſee, yet he ends in a triumph. <hi>Therefore I conclude here as I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the ſecond Section, where the Prince ſtands ſupreme,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:155066:32"/>
                  <hi>there Subjects may not by force of armes reſiſt, though he be exorbitant,</hi> &amp;c. p. 43. 'Tis true <hi>he concludes as he promiſed,</hi> but he hath not <hi>proved,</hi> as he <hi>promiſed;</hi> nor as we expected; for here is nothing, but that which fals to the ground with his ſuppoſals on which they are built; and which I have demoliſhed in the 4th Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> An Anſwer to the <hi>7th</hi> Section of his Replie, of places of Scripture out of the old Testament.</head>
               <p>HIs ſixt Section doth wholly concerne the <hi>Authour of the fuller <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> Anſwer,</hi> which I paſſe over, becauſe I am chargeable for no more then is my owne. And come to his <hi>ſeventh</hi> which containes an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of places alledged in this Queſtion out of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Where he begins confidently that there is <hi>no warrant for Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi> p. 56. and he yeelds two Reaſons why. 1. <hi>Becauſe the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of that Kingdom was ſuch as doth plainly exclude Reſiſtance.</hi> 2. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Prophets never call for it. Anſ.</hi> I grant it doth exclude it, as farre as in an <hi>abſolute Monarchie</hi> it may be excluded; and therefore there is no need of anſwering his Arguments. But yet let us conſider them ſith he is ſo large in them.</p>
               <p>To ſhew us the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of that Kingdome he brings, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.11. Where he ſayes we have it. <hi>For Samuel is commanded,</hi> v. 9. <hi>To tell the people (Jus Regis:)</hi> Now this <hi>jus Regis</hi> he makes a great matter of, and tels us <hi>it implies not a Right of doing ſuch unjuſt Acts, but a ſecuritie from Reſiſtance and force, if he does them.</hi> p. 56.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is no prejudice to the cauſe I defend, if I ſhould grant all he would worke out of this Text; for it prooves no farther then of that particular Kingdome, inducing no neceſſitie that all others muſt have the ſame Inſtitution. Alſo that which he concludes is but a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie for the Perſon of the Prince from force if he doe ſuch unjuſt Acts: which we grant him not only in that, but all Monarchies, even the moſt limited.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If he have any further reach, and would conclude out of it a <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall binding Ordinance</hi> of ſecurity from Reſiſtance entending even to ſubverſive Inſtruments of Will. The world will wonder at him for ſuch an audacious concluſion from ſuch premiſes. And we will look a little nearer to what he ſayes. All is grounded on his Interpretation
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155066:33"/>
of <hi>Jus Regis.</hi> Which he ſeeks to confirme by <hi>Calvins</hi> Authority.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for his <hi>Interpretation.</hi> I ſay the Originall words in this place are not to be tranſlated <hi>jus Regis,</hi> the <hi>Right of the King.</hi> Becauſe 1. There is another more fit ſignification of them: the words are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> now the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> being applied to unjuſt Acts, as here it is ought not to be rendred <hi>jus,</hi> but <hi>mos,</hi> not <hi>Right,</hi> but <hi>manner,</hi> as appeares by another place anſwerable to this, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeaking of <hi>Davids roving, This will be his manner,</hi> 'twere ridiculous to render it, this will be his <hi>right</hi> or <hi>priviledge.</hi> This out laſt Interpreters knowing, did willingly depart from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> whoſe Authour either ignorantly or inconſiderately did render it <hi>jus Regis;</hi> which this Doctour for his advantage doth here make ſo much of. 2. That rendring of it, cannot be juſtified by any other Text of Scripture; for wherſoever it is rendred <hi>Jus,</hi> it imports a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Right; not a priviledge or ſecuritie in ill doing. I challenge any skilfull in that tongue to bring one place where it is or can be ſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</p>
               <p>Then for <hi>Calvins</hi> Authority. I anſwer. 1. What if <hi>Calvin</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other deceived by the vulgar Latine, or ignorance of the extent of the Originall word, have rendred it ill; muſt that be a preſcription to others who know a better? 2. Neither doth <hi>Calvin,</hi> though he follow the <hi>Latine</hi> and render it <hi>jus,</hi> meane ſuch a <hi>jus</hi> as the Doctour doth, ſc. <hi>An abſolute immunity,</hi> or ſecurity from Reſiſtance: but onely from <hi>private men.</hi> For after he hath in all thoſe paſſages, which the Doctour cites, exempted Kings from violence, truly and piouſly ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging patience in Subjects under the injuries of their Princes, at length <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. (the ſame out of the which the Doctor brings his proofes) <hi>num.</hi> 31. He explaines himſelfe, <hi>De privatis hominibus ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per loquor,</hi> that all is to be taken of <hi>private men;</hi> not of the <hi>States of a Kingdome,</hi> in their publike meetings: never diſcerning of ſuch a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall immunitie, as the Doctour would put upon him to maintaine. And here I challenge not the Ingenuity, but the Conſcience of this Replier, who cites <hi>Calvin</hi> at large in the former place, as agreeing with him in this caſe of Reſiſtance, when he cannot be ignorant of the contrary, and therefore conceales his following words in the 31. <hi>num.</hi> Where he expreſſely teaches the ſame Truth which I have aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my <hi>Treatiſe.</hi> Heare him ſpeaking his judgement, <hi>De privatis hominibus ſemper loquor: Nam ſi qui nunc ſunt populares magiſtratus ad
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:155066:33"/>
moderandum Regum libidinem constituti (quales olim erant, qui Lacedemonijs regibus oppoſiti erant, Ephori, aut Romanis Conſulibus, Tribuni plebis; aut Athenienſium Senatui, Demarchi; &amp; qua e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam forte potestate (ut nunc res habent) funguntur in ſingulis regnis tres ordines, cum primarios conventus peragunt) adeo illos fenocienti Regum licentiae pro officio intercedere non veto, ut ſi Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus impotenter graſſantibus, &amp; humili plebeculae inſultantibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveant, eorum diſſimulationem nefaria perfidia non carere affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem, quia populi libertatem cui ſe, Dei ordinatione, Tutores poſitos norunt, fraudulenter produnt.</hi> He is cleare, that the Eſtates in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, not only may, but are <hi>Gods ordinance</hi> for it, and are bound to reſiſt, and not ſuffer the deſtruction of liberties, by exorbitating Princes; ſo that I may juſtly retort the Doctors words, p. 57. <hi>There can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſpoken more plainly for the power of reſiſtance in the Houſes of Parliament then this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then for his other reaſon from the 18. verſe, <hi>Ye ſhall cry out in that day, and the Lord will not heare you.</hi> As in my Treatiſe I called it <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequent;</hi> ſo alſo now: He is a good <hi>Logician</hi> which can draw his concluſion out of thoſe premiſes. But he blames me, <hi>p.</hi> 58. for ſaying it was an abſolute Monarchy, and <hi>cannot ſee how it can be ſo, according to my deſcription of abſoluteneſſe.</hi> Why not? <hi>In Abſolute Monarchy, there are no limits but the Monarchs own will; but theſe had a fixed judiciall Law,</hi> p. 59. I anſwer, That <hi>judiciall Law</hi> was no limits of their <hi>power;</hi> but of the <hi>exerciſe only;</hi> for the non obſervance of it by the King did not amount to an untying of the <hi>bond of ſubjection</hi> in the people. The <hi>Judiciall</hi> Laws being from God, not from any contract of the people, were in the ſame nature to that people, and for the time, with the <hi>Morall</hi> Laws; and in the ſame manner did limit their Kings, and no otherwiſe. But for the <hi>Abſoluteneſſe</hi> of that Monarchy, here <hi>Lyra</hi> (more faithfully cited,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lyra,</hi> in 1 Sam. 8.</note> then he did <hi>Calvin</hi> above) <hi>Conſtitutio Regis juxta poteſtatem ſibi conceſſum eſt duplex.)</hi> 1. <hi>Plena &amp; legibus abſoluta, prout legiſte de Imperatore dicere ſolent.</hi> 2. <hi>Cum poteſtate li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitata.</hi> Now ſayes he, the people ſinned, not ſimply in asking a King; but in asking a King of the firſt ſort, <hi>to judge them as the Nations,</hi> that is, <hi>abſolutely.</hi> He is expreſſe. 1. That limitation of power makes a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Monarch. 2. That <hi>Iſrael</hi> deſiring ſuch a Government as the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Nations, deſired an abſolute Monarch. And indeed as the define<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>morall</hi> Law doth not diſparage the Abſoluteneſſe of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:155066:34"/>
Monarch, becauſe it is from God, not the people; ſo did not their <hi>judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall,</hi> for the ſame reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>2</label> Next he comes to the peoples reſcue of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> p. 60. He may give their <hi>reſolute Oath</hi> what names pleaſeth him, <hi>a loving importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate violence, a ſouldierly boldneſſe,</hi> or the like; it was a peremptory expreſſion of no leſſe then an intent of reſiſtance, in caſe there had been need. Then for <hi>Davids</hi> purpoſe in having armed men about him; He ſays <hi>it was only to ſecure his perſon against the cut-throates of Saul,</hi> that is, <hi>againſt his private Emiſſaries. But who ſees not a large difference betweene ſecuring a mans ſelfe from private Emiſſaries, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the field with Armies against the Armies of the Prince,</hi> p. 61. Anſwer, 1. It is againſt reaſon, that he ſhould retaine an Army of 600. valiant Souldiers, yea a great Army, <hi>like the Hoſt of God,</hi> 1 Chron. 12.22. to ſecure himſelfe meerely againſt <hi>private Emiſſaries.</hi> 2. Let us grant him that there is a difference between ſecuring againſt private Emiſſaries, and the open Army: yet if he grant it lawfull to uſe force againſt one, he grants the cauſe by it, of all; for a warrant from an act of the Kings will is as valid to ſecure a few Emiſſaries, as a whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and Gods Ordinance in one man, is no more reſiſtible, then in a multitude. Then for <hi>Davids</hi> intent to keep <hi>Keylah</hi> againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> it is ſo evident, by the hiſtory, that I will ſay no more about it; but doe refer him to that which the <hi>Pleaders for defenſive Armes</hi> ſay about it. The Doctor ſeeks divers evaſions, to get out of the reach of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; but doth not ſatisfie himſelfe, much leſſe others, and therefore adds the fourth on which he muſt reſt when all is ſaid, <hi>That Davids example was extraordinary:</hi> Hereon he brings ſome things in him which were <hi>extraordinary;</hi> We grant it in many things; but we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it in this. If the Doctor will prove him to have a ſpeciall priviledge to reſiſt Gods ordinance in his Soveraign, more then other men; he muſt bring the grant and warrant for it: otherwiſe <hi>David</hi> muſt come under the common condition for this matter: He himſelfe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he had none for violating the perſon of his Prince; and ſure then he had none for violating the Authority of his Prince, conferred on <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Emiſſaries,</hi> if they had any. But in his <hi>p.</hi> 65. He layes hard at me, and <hi>challengeth not only my Reaſon for calling this a ſhufling An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but alſo my ingenuity, who confeſſe the people in that Government might not reſiſt; and yet doe urge theſe examples for Reſiſtance.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, 1. For my <hi>Reaſon:</hi> I have made it appeare I have reaſon to call
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:155066:34"/>
it ſo; is it not a meere <hi>evaſion,</hi> to affirme in him <hi>an extraordinary priviledge,</hi> and can bring no word, nor warrant for it? 2. For my <hi>ingenuity</hi> it is without cauſe challenged by him; for from the lawfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Reſiſtance of <hi>unreaſonable Acts of will,</hi> in an abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, where <hi>Reaſon is the Princes law;</hi> I may <hi>a fortiori</hi> conclude the lawfulneſſe of reſiſting of inſtruments of <hi>illegall Acts</hi> in a limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, where the <hi>Law of the Land is the Princes Law</hi> and bounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The</hi> 8. Section <hi>concerning Reſiſtance forbidden,</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw we are come to his principall ſtrength againſt Reſiſtance out <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. From whence nothing can be collected againſt any Reſiſtance, but that which is <hi>of the Powers, of the Ordinance:</hi> but that which I defend is of neither of them, therefore I have no cauſe to feare his inferences from that Text. Now ſuppoſing the truth which I have made good, that in a limited State the limitation is of the Power it ſelfe, and not only of the exerciſe; it followes evidently that in ſuch a State reſiſtance of deſtructive inſtruments, is neither of <hi>Power</hi> nor <hi>Gods Ordinance.</hi> I might therefore well omit that which at large here he ſpeakes of <hi>Reſiſtance of the Powers.</hi> The firſt part of the Section is ſpent in replying to the Exceptions of the <hi>Reverend Divines.</hi> The firſt thing I find which concernes me is, <hi>p.</hi> 77. I will therefore begin with him there. Where he accuſeth me <hi>that in my</hi> 59, 64, <hi>and</hi> 66. page <hi>of that Treatiſe, I grant they might not reſiſt in that Monarchy; but affirme that ſubjects may in this; and he brings me in giving two Reaſons for it.</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe Religion was then no part of the Lawes, but here it is.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe that was an Abſolute Monarchy, this a Limited and mixed,</hi> p. 77. But may I not here challenge both the ingenuity and conſcience of this <hi>Replyer.</hi> Did I ever grant that Gods <hi>Ordinance of Power</hi> might be reſiſted here; or give any <hi>Reaſons</hi> for ſo unreaſonable an Aſſertion? It would be tedious to repeate here, what I have ſaid there. Let the Reader ſee; if he pleaſe. I will recite the ſumme. 1. The Doctor affirmed, that in the Apoſtles time the <hi>Senate of Rome</hi> might challenge more then our <hi>Parliaments</hi> can now, I denied it, and gave my reaſon, <hi>ſc.</hi> That <hi>State</hi> was then devolved into a Monarchy by Conqueſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of this the Doctor ſpeakes not a word, perhaps he is now aſhamed of that compariſon. 2. He ſaid, there was greater <hi>cauſe</hi> of Reſiſtance then, than now. I anſwered. There
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:155066:35"/>
was then no <hi>cauſe</hi> at all: Not for <hi>Religion,</hi> being then, no part of the Law: Not <hi>Liberties;</hi> becauſe then that was paſt, the Government changed; and an Oath taken of abſolute ſubjection. Have I by theſe things granted a liberty of Reſiſtance of Gods Ordinance to this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and deny it to thoſe? No; Neither They, nor We; not that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved <hi>Senate;</hi> nor our free <hi>Parliaments,</hi> no cauſe, no priviledge can juſtifie this. Yea I aſcribe more to <hi>Gods Ordinance of Power,</hi> then He: He ſayes that in a limited ſtate we owe only <hi>paſſive ſubjection</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding commands of a Prince by promiſe limiting himſelfe in the uſe of his power. I ſay; though he ſin in exceeding ſuch promiſe; yet we owe him alſo <hi>Active obedience</hi> in ſuch commands which Gods Law forbids us not to be <hi>Active</hi> in. Neither doe I bring Doctor <hi>Bilſons</hi> teſtimony to prove that Religion was then no part of the Law, as he affirmes I doe, <hi>p.</hi> 77. but ſure he neither heeded what I had written, nor what himſelfe wrote. I laid down an Aſſertion that <hi>Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, is the <hi>Power</hi> and the <hi>Perſon</hi> of him which is ſupremely inveſted with that Power; and for this did I bring D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bilſon;</hi> who, explaining the Power there forbidden to be reſiſted, ſayes <hi>it is the Princes will not againſt his Lawes; but agreeing to his Lawes.</hi> Here he ſerves D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bilſon</hi> and other Divines, as before the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> teaches them a meaning contrary to their words: <hi>They meane ſuch ſtates as may by the knowne Laws uſe force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reſtraint:</hi> No ſuch meaning of his words: He makes no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>ſtates;</hi> but expounds the Text in queſtion, ſpeaking of <hi>Gods Ordinance</hi> in generall, in all <hi>Rulers:</hi> He knowes it well enough; and therefore addes, <hi>They were willing to excuſe as much as might be thoſe motions of the Proteſtants in France and the Low-Countries; but had they lived now, they would have spoken more cautelouſly.</hi> That is, They ſpake raſhly, wronged the truth, and reached their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to excuſe the commotions and rebellions of thoſe dayes. This is like a Doctor. But he likes the <hi>Homilie</hi> better then them all, <hi>that ſpeakes home,</hi> he ſayes; but what, he ſpeakes not, nor doe I anſwer. <hi>But he will try the force of this exception, becauſe I profeſſe, with</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, againſt Reſiſting of Authority though abuſed: And with</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bilſon, admit of reſiſting the Princes will againſt the Lawes: This is faſt and looſe, ſayes he.</hi> How ſo? In limited Monarchies, where the Prince hath no Authority beyond the Law: there an act beyond the Law is unauthoritative and meerely private; ſo that it is no <hi>abuſing of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:155066:35"/>
Authority;</hi> but an <hi>exceeding of Authority. Authority abuſed</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due acting of matters within its compaſſe, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Burrowes</hi> ſpeakes of, and that muſt not be reſiſted. But the <hi>Princes will</hi> acting againſt his Law, that is matters without the compaſſe of Authority is not Gods ordinance, ſayes D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and ſo may be reſted in its inſtruments. I ſtill ſay, let him prove ſuch acts to proceed from Authority, I will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Reſiſtance of their inſtruments, either the meaneſt <hi>Constable</hi> in the Land, or <hi>Souldier</hi> in the army. But how cloudes he this truth <hi>which is cleare as the day?</hi> 1. <hi>In that Government under which the Apoſtle lived, men might not reſiſt, though the Powers commanded contrary to Law, as oft they did: Not under the Arrian Emperours, though religion was then a part of the law,</hi> p. 78. Anſwer, 1. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> that learned Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> was of another judgement; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat. Antichrist,</hi> c. 7. In that Government he doth diſtinguiſh the Chriſtians carriage according to the diſtinction of times. At firſt before Religion was eſtabliſhed by Law, <hi>caedebantur, non caedebant,</hi> but after <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time when it was eſtabliſhed by Law. <hi>Caede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, non caedebantur.</hi> 2. We may grant it in that Government, becauſe it was abſolute, and the Laws were to the Prince but <hi>morall</hi> limitations of <hi>exerciſe:</hi> And, as I have often acknowledged, Acts of the Princes will, exceeding ſuch limitation, are <hi>poteſtative,</hi> and muſt not be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted: but it will not follow that therefore they are ſo, in governments where the Laws are limitations of the power it ſelfe, and <hi>exceeding</hi> acts are not <hi>poteſtative.</hi> Sure in thoſe times, as patient as the Chriſtians were, under their perſecutours, if their Religion and perſons had been aſſaulted without Authority, they would have made Reſiſtance: And this is all we affirme. 2. He makes two inquiries, 1. Whether the firſt Parliament in Qu. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reigne might have reſiſted her endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to change the eſtabliſhed Religion? Anſwer, They had ſinned in withſtanding the introduction of truth, and the Abolition of Falſhood; yet civilly and legally they might have done it: and abrogate a Law without the <hi>States</hi> ſhe could not. But, bleſſed be God there was no ſuch oppoſition; but a joynt conſent of all three Legiſlative Powers. 2. How can the putting down of <hi>Epiſcopall Government,</hi> be now ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified which ſtands by Law? Anſwer; It cannot, unleſſe there be a confluence of the conſent of all three; nor doe I believe it is intended without the Kings conſent, Unleſſe their conſtant doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to overthrow the liberties and Government of this Kingdome
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:155066:36"/>
into Arbitrarines doe prove them <hi>in all their ſort ſubverſive,</hi> and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with its ſafe being: Let therefore the Doctour and the reſt of them looke how they continue to maintain ſuch <hi>deſtructive Doctrins:</hi> for they will ſooner remove themſelves out of this Church, then the Subjects out of their ancient and juſt Liberties.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>2</label> At length let us ſee what he ſayes againſt the abſolute condition of the <hi>Romane Emperours. His other exception is, they were abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches, and therefore not to be reſisted,</hi> p. 79. <hi>Anſ.</hi> He doth me mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt injury: See my <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> I no where ſo argue; nor have I any need; for I equally affirm it of <hi>limited,</hi> as of <hi>abſolute power,</hi> that <hi>they ought not to be reſiſted;</hi> for they are equally Gods Ordinance, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> extends to <hi>the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are:</hi> Neither have I any need of that diſtinction to ſatisfie the Apoſtles Text: I aſſerted not the abſoluteneſſe of the Imperiall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie for any ſuch reaſon: but againſt his falſe affirmation, <hi>That that Senate in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls time, might challenge more then our great Councell can now.</hi> Here is apparent il dealing. But what can he oppoſe to what I ſaid about the <hi>abſolutenes</hi> of thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours? 1. <hi>It cannot be cleared that they were</hi> de jure <hi>abſolute. An.</hi> Yes, it can; according to the Doctors own grounds; for, 1. There was a full Conqueſt made by <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> in that fatall battell againſt <hi>Pompey</hi> not only of him;<note place="margin">Seneca. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam.</note> but in and with him, of the whole <hi>Senate,</hi> for <hi>in eo prima acies ſenatus fuit,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca.</hi> And the ſtrugling remainders of the <hi>free Senate</hi> were again vanquiſhed in that battle of <hi>Octavius</hi> againſt <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus.</hi> From that time all being proſtrate to his <hi>Will.</hi> 2. There was a ſubmiſſion to an <hi>Abſolute</hi> yoake. <hi>Romae ruere in ſervitium Conſules,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>1.</hi> ſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Patres, Eques,</hi> ſays <hi>Tacitus:</hi> yea the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> was ſo forward to it, that <hi>Tiberius</hi> was wont to ſay, as oft as he went out of the Court,<note place="margin">Ib. l. <hi>3</hi> ſ <hi>11</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>O homines ad ſervitutem natos!</hi> 3. There was alſo an eſtabliſhment of this ſubjection by an <hi>Oath:</hi> for the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> were brought under the ſame bond; and all this before S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion. That which he brings out of latter Authours, <hi>p.</hi> 80. of the <hi>Lex regia, quâ populus principi omne ſuum imperium &amp; potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem contulit:</hi> and his conjectures of it's not being before <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> time, is not worth a looking into: It was a formall complement of flattery to give that to him in words, which he had in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> ſo many yeares before. Alſo that of their forbearing the <hi>Diadem</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> of King, being contented only with that of <hi>Prince,</hi> was but the putting on a ſilken vaile upon a rough government. Vnder that ſmooth Title the people and Senate were held as much under, as the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:155066:36"/>
                  <hi>grand ſeigneur</hi> or <hi>Perſian</hi> now hold their Vaſſals. <hi>But they did perquam aiu magnam poteſtatis partem cum ſenatu communicare,</hi> p. 80. They did ſo; 'Twas their indulgence, or rather policie to impart it. It is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not by uncertaine Collections of late Authours; but by <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who is <hi>inſtar omneum</hi> in this buſineſſe;<note place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>1.</hi> ſ. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> ſ. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the firſt and beſt of them all, <hi>Poſito Triumviri nomine, conſulem ſe ferens, inſurgere paulatim, munia Magiſtratuum, ſenatus, Legum inſe trahere;</hi> and of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> that <hi>imaginem antiquitatis ſenatui praebebat.</hi> They conveyed their <hi>will</hi> through the old channell of the <hi>Senate,</hi> that it might reliſh the better with the people; yet at pleaſure did what they liſted, by them, and againſt them. 2. He ſayes, <hi>The Apoſtle in his reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reſistance hath no respect to the abſolute or limited condition of thoſe Roman Emperours.</hi> Nor doe I ſay, he hath: the Reaſon he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth is the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> which is true without diſtinction of the whole latitude of Power. 3. <hi>A limited condition doth no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a lawfullneſſe of reſistance for exorbitances, then an Abſolute,</hi> p. 82. I ſay not, that it doth; no condition can inferre a lawfulneſſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Power, though abuſed; but here is the <hi>priviledge</hi> of a people under a limited Monarch, his <hi>exceeding Acts</hi> are not abuſes of Power; but ſimply <hi>non poteſtative;</hi> and therefore their Agents may be reſiſted, without reſiſting the power; which is not ſo in an <hi>abſolute Rule;</hi> if there were no priviledge, why did men trouble themſelves in conſtituting Limitations, and Mixtures in a State: In a word, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he can prove Power in all Limited States, to be illimited: and all the <hi>Acts of will</hi> in the <hi>ſupreme</hi> to flow from <hi>Gods Ordinance:</hi> He la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in vain from that text, or any elſe to conclude againſt Reſiſtance of ſubverſive Inſtruments in a mixed Government.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> His ninth Section Anſwered: the Reaſons againſt Reſiſtance ſatisfied: and thoſe for Reſiſtance vindicated.</head>
               <p>WE are now come to his <hi>laſt Section:</hi> In examination of which <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> it will appeare that he hath as little <hi>Reaſon</hi> as <hi>Scripture</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt <hi>that Reſistance</hi> which I have aſſerted in my <hi>Treatiſe.</hi> Herein he doth two things. 1. Brings his <hi>Reaſons</hi> againſt Reſiſtance. 2. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to anſwer thoſe which I brought for it. But for more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent proceeding about both, we muſt diſtinctly call to mind the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> of what it is. 1. It is of Reſiſtance <hi>in this ſtate;</hi> that is, a ſtate
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:155066:37"/>
which I have proved to be <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>mixed</hi> in the very <hi>power</hi> it ſelfe. 2. It is only of <hi>Reſiſtance of deſtructive Inſtruments:</hi> Therefore if his Reaſons doe not reach to ſuch a Reſiſtance, they are not to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>Now againſt Reſiſtance the Doctour brings no fewer then <hi>nine Reaſons;</hi> In his firſt booke he had only <hi>five,</hi> here he hath made up in number, what they wanted in weight. I will in few words anſwer them diſtinctly, for many need not. 1. His firſt is from the <hi>wiſdom of God putting his people under Kings, without power of Reſiſtance; this ſhould be to us inſtead of a moſt forceable Reaſon,</hi> p. 84. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Well it may be <hi>inſtead of one;</hi> but it is not one. For 1. It was their deſire to be under an Abſolute Government, as their neighbour Countries were; and they offended God in it, as <hi>Lyra</hi> obſerves; therefore he giving them ſuch a King as they deſired; did not in his wiſdome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a <hi>binding forme</hi> for all people: I thinke the Doctour will not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme he did. 2. If he meane <hi>Reſiſtance of their Prince his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and perſon,</hi> I grant they were ſo put under; and ſo are we, and all that are put under <hi>Monarches;</hi> but if he mean the Acts of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will which were not Authoritative; I do denie it, and the former alledged inſtances prove they were not: and that is all I affirme in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Monarchies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The word of God gives no direction for it. The Prophets call not on the Elders for it: The new Teſtament commends patience in ſuffering for well-doing, Anſw.</hi> 1. In <hi>Civill</hi> matters <hi>negative reaſonings</hi> from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are not proving. 2. The word gives proving and imitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for it, as before: and indeed the Scripture doth every way ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie reſiſtance of cut-throats and private deſtructive Aſſaulters of Laws and Liberties, who have no Authority derived to them; and I defend no other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Apoſtle forbids Reſiſtance of the Powers, not from any compact of the people, but from the Ordinance of God.</hi> 'Tis true: for no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of people could eſtabliſh an unreſiſtible Power without the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of God. I acknowledge the Apoſtles ground for it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore allow no reſiſtance where there is <hi>Gods Ordinance</hi> to ſecure them, not for any abuſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>To be ſupreme and next to God implies a ſecurity from Reſiſtance,</hi> p. 85. I grant all; His <hi>Perſon,</hi> his <hi>Power</hi> is hereby ſecured: I condemn all riſing up againſt the <hi>King:</hi> but inſtruments of ſubverſion, have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:155066:37"/>
of the King in them: not his <hi>perſon</hi> nor <hi>Authoritie</hi> is riſen up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in them. For his conceits about <hi>jus Regis</hi> I have ſaid enough above. Neither doe I give to the <hi>Houſes</hi> the power of the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Ephori.</hi> They had an Authority over the very perſon of the King: which the <hi>Houſes</hi> claime not. I give them no more then <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> doth to the three Eſtates in their generall meetings. The Doctor well knowes what I will anſwer him; which he ſeeks to evade, 1. By affirming that <hi>the Reſiſting of Inſtruments acting by his Power, which he hath committed to them, is a reſisting of him,</hi> p. 86. 'Tis true, it is ſo; but we ſpeake of inſtruments, <hi>which act not by his power,</hi> that is, <hi>his Authoritie;</hi> but <hi>by his will</hi> in a courſe exceeding the Limitation of his Authority. Could he prove that a limited Prince could commit <hi>Power</hi> to doe acts without the bounds of his <hi>Power,</hi> the <hi>Queſtion</hi> were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, els he beggs it, but anſwers it not. 2. <hi>He would deſire me to look again upon the two Aſſertions of the Reverend Divines which I reject: He cannot conceive, how I can retaine my owne Aſſertion, and reject theirs.</hi> The Doctour hath a great mind to pick ſome contradiction in me; but ſtill failes in his endeavour. In good earneſt, doth he ſpeake really, when he ſayes, <hi>he cannot conceive,</hi> &amp;c. Well, let us looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on the <hi>two Aſſertions</hi> which I reject in them. 1. <hi>Governours who under pretence of Authoritie from Gods Ordinance diſturbe the quiet and godly life, are farre from being Gods Ordinance in ſo doing.</hi> 2. <hi>This tyrannie not being Gods Ordinance, they which reſiſt it even with armes, reſist not the Ordinance of God.</hi> Doe I defend any <hi>Aſſertions</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to theſe. Rather I aſſert in that Treatiſe, and here alſo the contrary. 1. <hi>Governours whither in abſolute or limited States, keeping within the meaſure of their power, may diſturbe the quiet and godly life, and yet be Gods Ordinance in that act, though croſſing the end of Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in it.</hi> 2. <hi>Powers though abuſed, yet being Gods Ordinance, they which reſiſt even in abuſive acts of it, reſiſt the Ordinance of God.</hi> Is here no difference? Cannot I retaine this Aſſertion, that <hi>exceeding Acts</hi> in limited Monarchie are not Gods Ordinance, and may in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments be reſiſted: And yet reject theirs, who maintain reſiſtance of <hi>Governours themſelves, in all acts of abuſed power?</hi> He makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>Acts exceeding bounds</hi> of power: and <hi>Acts of abuſed power:</hi> but of this more then enough before. 3. <hi>But he will anſwer more particularly,</hi> ſo he had need. What is it? <hi>He that beares the ſword, that is, has the ſupreme Power, gives Commiſſion to under-Miniſters for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:155066:38"/>
Juſtice; and to other Officers for the Militia: If therefore the Reſiſtance of thoſe though abuſing their Power, be a reſistance of the Power; ſo it is alſo of theſe. Anſw.</hi> I grant all: for it proceeds only of Miniſters <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing Power</hi> committed to them: not of Exceſſes of Power. I will retort it. Like as if when the <hi>ſupreme</hi> gives <hi>Commiſſion of Juſtice</hi> to a <hi>Judge;</hi> and he exceeding unto Acts without the compaſſe of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is but a private man in thoſe Acts and may be reſiſted: ſo if <hi>Commiſſion of Armes</hi> be given to a <hi>Generall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Subjection is due to a Prince, and the contrary forbidden without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of a good and bad Prince.</hi> I grant it, and give the reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are <hi>Gods Ordinance:</hi> but the Queſtion is of inſtruments of exceeding Acts, in which they are not Gods Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Good reaſon that he which hath the ſupreme Truſt, ſhould have the greateſt ſecuritie,</hi> p. 87. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is ſo; and ſo we grant him: for he hath a full ſecurity from all violence for both <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Authoritie,</hi> what ever exorbitance he breakes out unto. The people have not ſo: Every Subject being under the penalty of the Law for it's tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But the Doctor forgets his <hi>Clients,</hi> He is not arguing for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of <hi>Soveraignes;</hi> but <hi>Subiects,</hi> if they may be ſo called, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſubvert lawes and governments. But may we not alſo ſay, as it is good reaſon the ſupreme ſhould have the greateſt ſecuritie; ſo the people alſo ſhould have ſome ſecuritie; and not be expoſed like bruit beaſts to the ſavage luſts of every inſtrument of cruelty: having only this to comfort them, that they ſin in ſo doing? and ſo they doe, which with cruelty deſtroy even the bruit creatures.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>From the end and benefits of Government, for the enioying of which, it is good reaſon we ſhould beare with the exorbitances.</hi> Still he ſpeakes <hi>good reaſon;</hi> but nothing to the purpoſe; for we diſpute not of <hi>exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances</hi> of them who have the power; but of them who have <hi>no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> for what they doe. In exorbitances of leſſer nature, their will may ſecure inſtruments; but it is againſt reaſon that the benefits we have by their Government ſhould cauſe us to beare with them who would deſtroy their laws and government, for of ſuch is the Queſtion. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der here againe he brings <hi>Calvin,</hi> when he cannot but know that he is expreſſely for power of Reſiſtance in the Houſes: and no doubt <hi>P. Martyr,</hi> and the reſt follow <hi>Calvin</hi> in this.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Power of Reſiſtance in Subiects would be a remedie worſe then the diſeaſe, and more ſubverſive of a State, then if it wore left without it,</hi> p. 90.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:155066:38"/>
Why would it be ſo? <hi>It would be a continuall Seminary of jealouſies twixt Prince and people, and confuſion through the continuance of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes of Warre.</hi> Concerning this Argument of his, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 60. of my Treatiſe, where it is fully ſatisfied. 1. Who will believe the power of Reſiſting deſtructive inſtruments, ſhould be more deſtructive, then to let them alone without Reſiſtance? 2. Suppoſe <hi>by abuſe of this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> thoſe evils ſhould happen (for it ſo fals out to the beſt phyſicke, where the nocumentous humours are prevailing) yet this is but by <hi>accident:</hi> ſuch Power <hi>per ſe</hi> and of its owne nature tends to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of ſubverſion. On the contrary by woefull experience, this Doctrine of the unreſiſtibleneſſe of ſuch men, hath nurſed up a brood of audacious projectours, and where it is taught, a <hi>ſtate</hi> will never be without them. Whereas, if the Truth were knowne it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine the ſpirits of wicked men from <hi>paracide</hi> and <hi>State ſubverſion.</hi> Neither can any thing be more miſchievous, then to teach an impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for projectours, and Agents of miſchiefe: and he hath not the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a man who argues otherwiſe. 3. Neither can this doctrine, as the <hi>Replier</hi> traduces it, extend to the <hi>depoſing of Princes,</hi> or the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing</hi> of their Authority, for it concernes only their <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> not their <hi>Perſons;</hi> their Abſolute, extra-legall <hi>Will;</hi> not their <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> And for <hi>iealouſies,</hi> they will be more bred by that Doctrine which gives the <hi>Prince</hi> a Power to undoe the <hi>State,</hi> then by that which terminates <hi>both;</hi> and gives <hi>neither</hi> a power to ſubvert the <hi>other;</hi> Danger is the nurſe of jealouſie: that which takes away <hi>power of hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> takes away <hi>Danger;</hi> and ſo removes <hi>iealouſies:</hi> but indeed ſuch which have a plot of breaking up the hedge of Government, and bringing lawleſſe powers into a State, care not for having ſuch a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in thoſe <hi>Houſes</hi> whom it would cauſe them to feare, and looke on with <hi>continuall jealouſies.</hi> The <hi>Homily</hi> of Rebellion is in vaine ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt that which is no rebellion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The laſt and weakeſt of all is that of <hi>the hearts of Kings being in Gods hands,</hi> Prov 21.1. and that of <hi>Gods Covenant with David and his ſeed,</hi> 2 Chron. 6.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.17. How the Doctor can draw hence a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion againſt Reſiſtance of ſubverſive inſtruments, I cannot imagine. Sure if theſe Texts had any proving force in them, they had not been brought ſo late: Rather then place had been in the former Section, where in the cloſe he ſaies, <hi>He choſe onely to inſiſt on thoſe Texts which are fit to beare argument</hi> but here he hath broke his word, yet he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, for he had no better.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:155066:39"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> At length he comes to my Arguments brought <hi>for Reſiſtance.</hi> If they be not more concluding then his, would they had never ſeen the light, nor come to the eye of any judicious man. Let us ſee what he hath to ſay to them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Reſiſtance is lawfull which is no Reſiſtance of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God; but this of ſubverſive inſtruments is not, being neither of the Perſon nor Authority of the Prince. He ſayes, <hi>He hath propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and anſwered this above under his third and fourth Reaſons.</hi> And there I doubt not but the invaliditie of his <hi>Anſwer</hi> doth plainly appeare.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Without this Power of Reſiſtance all limitation of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is vaine; and all formes reſolve into that which is arbitrary. He tels me, <hi>My Argument is inconſequent by my owne deſcription of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarchie: ſo that the reſtraint of a limited Monarch is Legall and Morall, not forceable and Military,</hi> p. 93. I anſwer, I deſcribe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and Abſolute Monarchie not by <hi>Force;</hi> but the having or not having <hi>a bounds</hi> of Will; but how abſurd it is when the <hi>diſtinctive con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit</hi> in the definition of a limited Monarch, is <hi>a Law terminating his will</hi> to take it of a <hi>morall</hi> terminating, which is common to all, not only Monarches but men? Eſpecially ſith I explaine my ſelfe ſo fully afterwards, as I doe, there <hi>p.</hi> 7. in the three degrees of abſoluteneſſe. But I have above enough diſcovered the fraud and falſhood of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of <hi>Legall</hi> and <hi>morall</hi> Limitation; and have prooved that to give a Limited Monarch only a morall Limitation, is to reſolve all into Abſolute and Arbitrary, for the moſt abſolute under heaven hath morall limitation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such Power is due to a publique State for its preſervation which is allowed to a particular perſon. He anſwers, <hi>this is not univerſally true.</hi> Why not? a State is more worthy, and comprehends a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of particular men: doth <hi>number</hi> detract from their <hi>priviledge?</hi> He would ſeeme to have reaſon for his deniall: <hi>A private man hath by the law of nature power of ſelfe-preſervation againſt the force of another private man; yet is this power yeelded up in regard of Civill Power, and not to be uſed againſt perſons indued with ſuch power,</hi> p. 94. 1. He ſtill ſpeakes Truth; but not to the Queſtion: which is not of perſons <hi>indued with civill power;</hi> but ſuch as we have proved to have <hi>no power;</hi> grant them <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with power,</hi> neither a particular man: or a whole Community muſt reſiſt them: but having none, it is much more allowable in a <hi>publique</hi> ſtate, then a <hi>particular</hi> perſon. 2. He ſpeakes of a <hi>power yeelded up,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:155066:39"/>
as if in all governments the people doe ſimply yeeld up all power of Reſiſtance into a full ſubjection unto all Acts of the Princes will: Whereas we have prooved, that in limited Governments it is not ſo: but to the Princes Will meaſured and regulated by a Law; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have that power ſtill, in reſpect of all inſtruments of acts of Will not ſo regulated.</p>
               <p>But it is obſervable, that <hi>p</hi> 95. the Doctour is beaten off from his owne grounds, and yeelds up in the <hi>Cloſe</hi> of his booke a full Victory to Truth. Which will appeare if we looke backe to his firſt booke, and <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. where he propoſeth the Queſtion in his own termes, <hi>whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if a King be bent or ſeduced to ſubvert Religion, Laws and Liberties, Subjects may take up armes and reſiſt.</hi> He undertakes to maintaine the <hi>Negative;</hi> and here was the beginning of the controverſie. Now ſee in this <hi>Replie</hi> how he is ſunck and ſtollen off from that which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke to defend; and upon the matter grants us the <hi>Cauſe.</hi> For, 1. By <hi>bent or ſeduced to ſubvert,</hi> he tels us, he means not a purpoſe of the mind, <hi>but doing many Acts arbitrarily tending to ſubuerſion;</hi> as if he would yeeld, that (ſuppoſing him bent, that is purpoſing and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it in his mind and courſe) he might be reſiſted. 2. Nay, by <hi>[bent to ſubvert]</hi> he does not meane ſo much as <hi>Acts ſubverſive;</hi> but onely <hi>Acts tending to ſubverſion of themſelves; for the frame of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Lawes cannot be ſubverted without the conſent of the two Houſes.</hi> So that now the Queſtion is rather, <hi>Whither ſubverſion be poſſible</hi> by ſuch inſtruments; then <hi>whether their Reſiſtance be lawfull:</hi> Sure it were pitty to diſturbe them by Reſiſtance in an impoſſible worke: Let them run on rather till they ſee their owne vanity and folly: but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſhould bring it to paſſe; then it would be too late to come to this Doctor and tell him, he was deceived, and did deceive. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly thoſe great Polititians who have had this deſigne in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſo many yeares, are not of his mind. Yea, ſuppoſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done <hi>without the conſent of the Houſes;</hi> yet the Doctour can tell us in another caſe, that where there is an unreſiſtible power, <hi>Conſent cannot</hi> long <hi>be wanting.</hi> What then; will he yeeld us a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Reſiſtance, if we can proove ſuch a deſigne poſſible?</p>
               <p>Here alſo becauſe the Doctor ſayes <hi>this liberty which I allow a State for its preſervation, tends rather to its ſubverſion,</hi> p. 94. and every where calumniates me as an inducer of <hi>confuſion,</hi> and <hi>Anarchie,</hi> and my Aſſertions as opening a way to <hi>Rebellion.</hi> It concernes me effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:155066:40"/>
to vindicate my ſelfe, and the truth which I maintaine from theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions; and make it appeare that the power of Reſiſtance I defend is not a remedy worſe then the diſeaſe of ſubverſion. Which I can doe no better way, then by a poſitive ſetting downe the naked truth which I averre in this and the former Treatiſe; and ſhew how it ſhuts up every way to theſe evills which he layes uncharitably to my charge. 1. I aſſert no forceable Reſiſtance in any caſe but <hi>ſubverſive</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme.</hi> 2. Subverſive and extreme caſes reſpect either particular men; or the whole ſtate and Government. For <hi>particular men</hi> even in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme caſes of ſtate or life, I allow no <hi>publike</hi> Reſiſtance: but appeale if it may be had; or if not, yet no <hi>publike</hi> Reſiſtance: for whether the wrong be done him by inferiour or ſuperiour Magiſtrates, either it is, 1. Under forme and courſe of Law, and power committed them; and then to reſiſt, is to reſiſt the <hi>power.</hi> 2. Or without all forme and courſe of Law and power committed to them: and then a man values his ſtate and life too high, to make <hi>publike</hi> reſiſtance, and bring on the ſtate a <hi>generall diſturbance</hi> for his <hi>private</hi> good, and ſins, though not againſt Gods ordinance of Power, in this caſe, yet againſt the <hi>publike peace and weale.</hi> For the <hi>whole ſtate or government,</hi> and the laſt caſes of its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, of which the Doctor puts the Queſtion. 1. I condemne all force uſed againſt the Perſon of the ſupreme, or his Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in any inferiour Miniſters thereof. 2. I averre not publike force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reſiſtance of Miniſters of acts of will which are only <hi>actuall inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> or <hi>exceſſes of limitation;</hi> and not ſuch as plainly argue a <hi>bent of ſubverſion,</hi> and <hi>apparent danger</hi> thereof, if prevention be not uſed: ſo that the Doctor goes from the Queſtion, and comes home to me, when he ſayes here that he ſpeakes only of the former ſort. 3. I affirme not force in this utmoſt caſe to be aſſumed by <hi>private men</hi> againſt deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive inſtruments of the Princes will: as if any man were warranted on his own imagination of publike danger to raiſe forces for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the <hi>Courts of Juſtice,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>the ſupreme Court,</hi> to whom the <hi>conſervation of Government and Law</hi> is committed, and a Power not only to reſiſt, but alſo cenſure and puniſh its violaters, much more its ſubverters without regard of <hi>number</hi> or <hi>warrant,</hi> (The Law ſuppoſing no warrant can be in ſuch caſe) This is the power of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which I have aſſerted: and it this be inducing of <hi>civill warre,</hi> or a <hi>way to ſubverſion</hi> and <hi>Rebellion:</hi> It is a <hi>warre</hi> raiſed by <hi>defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Law,</hi> againſt <hi>ſubverters of Law:</hi> A <hi>Rebellion</hi> raiſed by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:155066:40"/>
having Authority,</hi> againſt <hi>inſtruments of arbitrarineſſe having no authority: A reſiſtance tending to ſubverſion,</hi> but of none but <hi>ſubverters.</hi> 'Tis good reaſon then, it ſeemes, if deſtroyers grow to the number and ſtrength of an Army, for Magiſtrates to let them alone, and not raiſe armes to ſuppreſſe them, leſt they open a way to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and bring on the miſeries of a civill Warre. This is the Doctors <hi>preſervative</hi> Doctrine, and my contrary is <hi>destructive.</hi> 4. I argued from the <hi>end</hi> of the inſtitution of the Houſes, and their intereſt in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws, and preſerving the frame. He ſayes <hi>this is grounded on my falſe ſuppoſall of their being joyned with the King in the very ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power,</hi> p. 96. Anſwer, I have juſtified that ſuppoſall; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted his ſtrange boldneſſe in denying it againſt the <hi>Kings,</hi> and ſo many <hi>Parliaments</hi> direct affirmations; and deſire the reader to take notice, that this is <hi>Calvins</hi> argument for Reſiſtance, in the place above recited, how ever the Doctor doth make ſo light of it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. From the power of <hi>inferiour Courts</hi> to puniſh violaters of Law, though pretending a warrant of the Kings will for it. He ſayes <hi>this Argument is inconſequent to prove power of rayſing Armies to oppoſe the Forces of their Soveraigne.</hi> He haſtens to a concluſion, and weighs not much what he anſwers. I ſay it concludes <hi>inevitably:</hi> for if the Kings warrant to violate Law, will not priviledge <hi>one</hi> from force of juſtice, then not a <hi>hundred,</hi> not <hi>an Army</hi> of violaters. Their <hi>multitude</hi> makes the danger <hi>greater,</hi> and the Kingdome <hi>more unhappy;</hi> not Malefactors <hi>more priviledged. The forces of the Soveraigne</hi> in truth, are the <hi>Forces raiſed to defend his Government;</hi> not thoſe which are raiſed to ſubvert it. They are his, which have his <hi>Authoritative will;</hi> not thoſe which have only his <hi>arbitrary.</hi> If ever Reaſons did demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate a truth, I am confident theſe <hi>five</hi> have made good, <hi>The power of the estates in Parliament to reſiſt ſubverſive inſtruments,</hi> be they more or fewer.</p>
               <p>Thus have I traced this Authour through his <hi>Reply;</hi> and whether <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> I have not ſufficiently vindicated my <hi>Treatiſe</hi> from it, I referre my ſelfe to the conſcience of every one who hath the <hi>underſtanding</hi> of a <hi>judicious</hi> man; and the <hi>impartiality</hi> of a <hi>juſt man.</hi> In my cap. 8. <hi>is a moderate debate</hi> of the preſent contention; and divers <hi>Petitions ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to pacification</hi> if it had been poſſible: but he toucheth not on that chapt. His diſcourſe ſhewes him to have nothing to doe with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration;</hi> nor doth deſire <hi>Peace,</hi> but on the termes of a full dedition
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:155066:41"/>
into the hands of ſubverſive inſtruments. I have done with him: <hi>He reſolved,</hi> I Anſwered. <hi>He hath replyed.</hi> I have returned on it. I am even with him; and in truth above him, I am ſure. Now I deſire to ſpin out this contention no longer. Yet if he, or any elſe pleaſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne, I wiſh he would ſave himſelfe, and me a labour: to let alone the booke; and deale only with the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>; and 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapters concerning the Doctors ſuppoſals; if he can make good them; and invalidate mine, as much as in me lieth, I will yeild him the cauſe: but I judge it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, if I know what is impoſſible. <hi>The God of ſpirits allay the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men from this extreme oppoſition: And give ſuch a iſſue to theſe wofull warrs, that the ſcepter of Chriſt, the Gospell of Peace may be fully ſubmitted to and maintained by a King enjoying inviolate his due ſoveraignty; and a People their due and lawfull liberties,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PHIL. 4.5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let your moderation be known unto all men: The Lord is at hand.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:155066:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
